<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prudence the first of the foure cardinall virtues. Written by Sr. Miles Sandis, Kt</title>
            <title>Prima pars parvi opusculi</title>
            <author>Sandys, Miles, Sir, 1600 or 1601-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 144 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851870</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prudence the first of the foure cardinall virtues. Written by Sr. Miles Sandis, Kt</title>
                  <title>Prima pars parvi opusculi</title>
                  <author>Sandys, Miles, Sir, 1600 or 1601-1636.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, William, fl. 1617-1650, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44], 253, [11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W: Sheares, in Brittaines Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue of "Prima pars parvi opusculi", with letterpress title page cancelled by an engraved title page signed "W.M. scu:", i.e. William Marshall. Variant: letterpress title page uncancelled.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Copies reported lack the cancellations and additions found in some copies of STC 21731.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prudence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a female personification of prudence holding a bird in one hand and three entwined snakes in the other, with another bird on her shoulder</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PRVDENCE The first of the Foure Cardinall Virtues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Written by S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Miles Sandis K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed for W: Sheares, in Brittaines Burſe</p>
                  <p> W.M. ſcu:</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>GYNDANES</hi> TO ABAVCVS; That is, MILES SANDYS <hi>Preſents his beſt Love,</hi> Reſpect, Service, or what you will in this Senſe, to <hi>Henrie Sandys.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My <hi>Alter Ego,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it may ſtand with Truth, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> for everie day
<pb facs="tcp:17163:4"/> through the yeare, made ſome good Law for the Common-wealth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting two daies in the moneth of <hi>Februarie,</hi> in which hee was ledde away by the ſenſualitie of pleaſures from the Publicke good; (the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of which neglect, cauſed the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Prince to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge the Moneth of two dayes:) Or that <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatus</hi> (for which Storie fames him) did, from the day of his Birth, to the day of his Death, penne a ſheet of Paper
<pb facs="tcp:17163:4"/> for every day, through his life at leaſt; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, That wherein his Youth had beene defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, his Age had made it good; And, that the fruits of his riper yeares had ſupplied the ſlips of his Minoritie. If either of theſe Inſtances will carry truth, then, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe, I am not to bee blamed for that ſmall ſpace of late, wherein I have been wholy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Studie, and Reading: And amongſt my buſied thoughts, have made choice of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17163:5"/> Poeſie, <hi>Nulla dies ſine lineâ;</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee taxed, unleſſe it bee by thoſe, who will ſay, there was <hi>Nulla linea ſine die.</hi> What to write of, I made my Books my Counſellours: for they were ever ſo open hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mee, that they would acquaint mee with others, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme mee of mine owne Faults without Flattery. They told me, Divinity was too deepe for my Capacitie, Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie too laborious, Hiſtorie ſo various, and
<pb facs="tcp:17163:5"/> ſo full fraught with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, that once begun, never at an end. And ſo <hi>ab Arte ad Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, à Scientiâ ad Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, &amp;c.</hi> At laſt, in this time of ſcarcitie, they adviſed mee to write <hi>De Moribus.</hi> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I conceived, the <hi>Foure Cardinall Virtues</hi> were moſt neceſſarie, ſince they are the Heads of Morall Philoſophie. But, becauſe the name of Philoſophie ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth odious to ignorant eares, I thinke it not amiſſe to inſtruct their
<pb facs="tcp:17163:6"/> Simplicitie, in telling them in the words of Saint <hi>Auguſtine, If Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers have ſpoken that which is true, we ought not onely to beleeve it, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it as our owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Divine, a Naturall, and a Morall Philoſophy.</p>
            <p>The Theological Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy is that Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or Rudiment of Knowledge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning God, which may bee obtained by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge may be truely ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:17163:6"/> Divine in reſpect of the Object. As for the Naturall, I will leave it, for the moſt part, to the Naturaliſts. And for the Morall; If it pleaſe you to obſerve it in its Sapientiall part. Read <hi>quod ſequitur,</hi> I doubt not to give ſome ſatisfaction herein, ſince all Profeſsions are from Philoſophy ſerved and ſupplied.</p>
            <p>That I have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled my Diſcourſe, I want not Authority for it: <hi>Plato</hi> mixed Philoſophy with Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy:
<pb facs="tcp:17163:7"/> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> with <hi>Logicke: Proclus</hi> with the Mathematickes. Reade Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Bernard, Gregory,</hi> I dare ſay, almoſt all the Fathers have linked Morality with Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Nay goe to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Text, and you ſhall find golden Philoſophy inſerted in holy Writ: I have heard it delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Pulpit by a reverend Penman, That <hi>Solomon</hi> reduced his three Divine Tracts to the order of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy: As if in his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17163:7"/> he had tutored his Sonne with Morality; In his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> by a Didacticall Diſcourſe, he had read a Naturall Philoſophy Lecture; And in his Diviner <hi>Canticles,</hi> had framed a ſpeculative ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Dialogue: Nor was his Reaſon to bee diſallowed of, ſince it did proceed from that learned Expoſitor, <hi>Hugo de Sancto Victore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now firſt, if it ſhould bee asked wherefore I write, ſince I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to build my Houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:17163:8"/> before my ſtones are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; like an ill Cooke, ſerving up my Diſhes before they bee ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. I anſwer, that the Activeſt part of Man is his Mind; I thought it not fit, that it ſhould be eaten away with the Ruſt of Idleneſſe; Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being the Grave of Living Man, a thing wherein life dieth; the uſe of Bookes being to encreaſe Knowledge, and to bring forth the Dead ſpeaking with the Living The Dew of Heaven looſeth it ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:17163:8"/> in the Earth, unleſſe it bee collected into ſome Receptacle: So learning, and Knowledge ſoone periſh, and vaniſh into Oblivion, if they be not preſerved in Bookes. Secondly, why I quote my Authors, it being thought by ſome Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danticall. I anſwer, I would not bee behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſo many Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, without giving them ſome note under my hand. And if miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Criticks will but looke backe, and ſearch Antiquity, they may
<pb facs="tcp:17163:9"/> find that in thoſe flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing yeares in the nonage of <hi>Nero,</hi> the Common-wealth was never better governed, then it was by <hi>Seneca</hi> a Pedant: So was it in the minority of <hi>Gordia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> by <hi>Meſellinus:</hi> Nay goe to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> you may find <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> and <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> were both Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danticall Friers, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver better government then in their times. I have endeavoured to hit the Truth, therby to muzzle the Mouth of
<pb facs="tcp:17163:9"/> Contradiction: For as I would not pleaſe any in their faults, ſo I would not bee faulty to pleaſe any. Laſtly, why I direct this Virtue to you; It is not becauſe I think you want it, but, by reaſon of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with it, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed you to bee a fitter Iudge of it. True it is, the vanity of moſt Writers hath beene to throwe their wit in Inke, as Mad men doe ſtones in the Aire, not caring whom they hit;
<pb facs="tcp:17163:10"/> Being free of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brokers, uttering none but ſtollen Wares, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Acknowledgment; making their Braines Quivers of Ieſts, travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in their ſtudies till they are delivered of the Aire. What I have done, I thinke I may avouch, ſince I was ſo thrifty, as not to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe papers, leſt I ſhould be forced to pay more for the Silence, then for the Worke.</p>
            <p>In that I write not Great words, nor High-borne
<pb facs="tcp:17163:10"/> Language, it is, becauſe I have ſeldome found a Verbaliſt a Materialiſt; great Words being commonly atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on by little Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. To pleaſe all men in one thing is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible; For the ſame cauſe, that made <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus</hi> laugh, made <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus</hi> weepe. The skilfulleſt <hi>Fiſherman,</hi> that ever was, could never pleaſe all Fiſh with one baite; Nor the ſolideſt Writer all men with one Booke.
<pb facs="tcp:17163:11"/> The generall Fancy of the World being like <hi>Plutarchs</hi> Moone, who deſired her Taylor to make her a Peticote, but before the Taylor had brought it home, the Moone was in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Quarter.</p>
            <p>Now are there not ſome detracting <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſſes,</hi> who (like the Booke-worme) live on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deſtroy Learning, lending long eares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them they love not? And perhaps ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing me to bee like a
<pb facs="tcp:17163:11"/> Statue in the High-way, directing others, but not following one ſtep my ſelfe: Or like <hi>Noahs</hi> Carpenter, building an Arke to ſave others, yet cannot helpe my ſelfe, taxing mee as <hi>Diogenes</hi> did Muſitions, ſaying, They could skilfully tune, and order the ſtrings of their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of their Minde were diſordered, and quite out of tune. I am apt to beleeve this and more: For what Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="tcp:17163:12"/> hath entred into the hive of their hearts, which they have not converted into poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Nor is this any wonder, Truth had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver but ill-favoured At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants; <hi>Veritas odium parit.</hi> Goe on then; dart your quills of Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, with the Porcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, at him, that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you not. I muſt reſt ſatisfied, ſince it is not in my power to tie looſe Tongues; yet I wiſh, That all Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous power may looſe
<pb facs="tcp:17163:12"/> its ſting: That Envie may flie mens Soules, That it be blinde. Yet I ſhall neither feare, nor care. Onely I will ſay to them that uſe it, as <hi>Damodoclus</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Mileſians,</hi> That they were no Fooles, yet they did the ſame things, that Fooles did.</p>
            <p>As for you, unto whom I Dedicate it, if my paines ſhould bee ſo fortunate, as to bring forth ſuch iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues, as may imprint
<pb facs="tcp:17163:13"/> the leaſt Conſolation in your heart, then, perhaps, I will goe on with the three lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cardinalls; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that my Penne is but as a Cypher in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmeticke, which, without the Figure of your Approbation, adds nothing. If not, that Penne, that wrote this, ſhall ever be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to a Standiſh. If it pleaſe you, I am pleaſed. Howſoever, I have given Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to one, that heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:17163:13"/> approoves that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Reſolution:
<q>
                  <l>Haec, ſi diſplicui, fuerint ſolatia nobis:</l>
                  <l>Haec fuerint nobis praemia, ſi placui.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PIVS IESVS</p>
            <p> HENRICVM SANDYS</p>
            <p> AB HOSTIBVS</p>
            <p> TVEATVR.</p>
            <p> MDCVVVVVVIIII.</p>
            <p> 1634.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Miles Sandys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:14"/>
            <head>TO MY HONOVRED TVTOR Doctor <hi>Aſtley</hi> Warden of All Soules Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to ſchollers, and among them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provedly received for
<pb facs="tcp:17163:15"/> Truth; That Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are more obliged for Education, then for Birth; the one gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the bare Being, the other the well-Being. The firſt J had by Nature: As for the other, In thoſe <hi>Annis pube ſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> when J was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Protection, you adviſed, and ſet me forward with that care, which might
<pb facs="tcp:17163:15"/> have made me enjoyed it by Art, had I beene ſo diligent a Scholler, as to have followed your highly to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended Inſtructions. What I have now wrote, you know, is all in Generalls, which none ſhould take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions at. Yet leſt ſurmiſing Iudgements ſhould endeavour to rivet Generalls into the narrow and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:17163:16"/> compaſſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, J have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for borne divers notes of conſequence. Yet whether in thoſe now urged, or in the other ſuppreſſed, J vow and proteſt the ſyncerity of my intent, that J never meant to make any particular perſon the ſubject of them, to whom, either by the lawes of God or Nature, I ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:17163:16"/> bound either in duty or ſervice: though falſe murmures have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced me ſo farre, I call my Judge in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the witneſſe of what my Pen ſets forth, that it was (without any oblique glancing toward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) but a bare innocent Eſſay of my weake endeavours, and a teſtimonie, that you ſent mee not from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he
<pb facs="tcp:17163:17"/> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie ſo illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as not to ſpeake (though but imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly) my Mother tongue. Nay let ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy light on mee, and mine <hi>ad perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> if I deliver not the naked Truth of my harmeleſſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction then this, if I would, I could not give. And as for others, if there be
<pb facs="tcp:17163:17"/> any ſo ſimple, as to demand it, they ſhall have no other then this. That I ſlight their thoughts more, then they can, or dare my words. Yet let them know, that, if J had been bent to have wrot Spleene, I would have penned it with ſuch Characters of blood, as ſhould have cauſed another De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge to have waſhed
<pb facs="tcp:17163:18"/> them out,</p>
            <p>Nor ſhould my pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence have preſented her ſelfe to a publike view without her Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociats, had not the uſurped libertie of ſome endeavoured to have wronged mee in her, her in mee; Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the Authour, becauſe they have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle acquaintance with the Subject.</p>
            <p>True it is, where
<pb facs="tcp:17163:18"/> injuries are done, Mens thoughts are commonly of ill dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: the nature of wrong being not of an eaſie concoction. Yet none ſhould wound Reputation, nor ſet too high price on weakneſſe. Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors venemous ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are as Figures drawne in water, whoſe malicious words not prevailing are but
<pb facs="tcp:17163:19"/> like the Fooles bolts ſhot upright, which in the fall in danger their owne heads. For ſuch Malefactors, J conceive, neglect is the beſt revenge, it being greater glory to avoyd Injuries by Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying. And here J will make choice of <hi>Plato's</hi> anſwer (if neede require it)
<pb facs="tcp:17163:19"/> who receiving op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious words from his Enemies, being deſired, he ſhould not returne the like inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, anſwered, Hee had not ſo much idle time, as to remember them.</p>
            <p>But concerning your ſelfe, for your paines and care for my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>tàm mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quàm doctrinâ,</hi> J muſt give thankes.
<pb facs="tcp:17163:20"/> Thankes J render as freely from my Heart as can be expreſſed by Tongue or Pen.</p>
            <p>May then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of your minde enjoy what it moſt deſires, or deſerves. May you live till time ſhall ſicken with your age, And when Death comes, May you poſſeſſe the hope of your well ſpent life in Heaven. Such is
<pb facs="tcp:17163:20"/> the Prayer of your <hi>quondam</hi> Pupil, and ever ſervant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Miles Sandys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:21"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader,</hi> I here ſend forth Prudence to your view; if you bee wiſe, you may embrace it, Jf not, you may let it alone. If you commend it, I am not therewith puffed up: If you diſpraiſe it, I am not therewith dejected. An Eſſay it is of ſome few ſtolne houres, that might have beene otherwiſe loſt,
<pb facs="tcp:17163:22"/> or worſe ſpent: And if diſtaſtfull Critickes ſhall miſ-interpret the innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of my harmleſſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I ſhall but reply, and play with their ſporting Cenſures, as doth <hi>Ben Iohnſon</hi> in his Play-workes.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Praiſe or Diſpraiſe is to me alike,</l>
               <l>Th'one doth not ſtroake me, nor the other ſtrike.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:22"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed> Tho: Weeks R: P: D. Epiſcopo Lond: Cap: Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:23"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17163:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>AN INTRODVCTION to the foure Cardinall VIRTVES.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to write like to the report of a ſuperficiall Traveller, who, paſſing thorow the confines of ignote Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, regiſters onely the continents. I in like manner, being but ſuperficially read,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17163:24"/> and preſenting that which ſlight knowledge cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly performe, like to ſuch a Traveller muſt record by view, by reading, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by report; report of Centaurs and Gorgons I liſt not, I have ſeene no new found Land, nor read of Magellanick Earth, I ſpeake of no ſuch Parts. <hi>Partes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum mihi ſunt,</hi> my Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſhall be reaſonable and confined onely to the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of reaſonable man, ſuch as inchoats his happineſſe in this world, and conſummates his bliſſe hereafter. <hi>Virtutes ſunt,</hi> and thoſe Cardinall; Cardinall if <hi>Peraldus</hi> miſtake not for foure Cauſes.<note place="margin">Peral.</note> 
               <hi>Primò propter ſtabilitatem, ut Cardo ſtabilis manet licet oſtium in eo vertatur: ſic hae quatuor
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17163:24"/> virtutes ſtabiles ſunt, licet ea circa quae verſantur ſint in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabilia. Secundò quia ſicut oſtium Cardini innititur: Sic tota converſatio bona his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor virtutibus innititur. Tertiò propter praeeminentiam primae ſunt reſpectu aliarum. Quartò propter principalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: caeterae enim virtutes ad has aliquo modo reducuntur.</hi> Firſt, for the ſtability, for as the hinge of a doore remaineth firme and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, although the doore be turned theron: So theſe foure Virtues are firme and unmoveable, although thoſe things about which they are converſant, are moveable, uncertaine and inſtable. Secondly, becauſe as the doore hangs on the hinge, ſo all good converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17163:25"/> depends on theſe foure Virtues. Thirdly, for their Praeeminence, theſe being the firſt in reſpect of other Virtues. Fourthly, for their Principality: for other vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues ſome way or other are reducible unto theſe.<note place="margin">D. Hier. D. Ambr.</note> 
               <hi>Dicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hae quatuor virtutes Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinales ab Hieronymo &amp; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſio, propterea quod ut fores Cardinibus, Sic illis omnis moralis vitae honeſtas, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitas fulciatur.</hi> Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> and Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led theſe foure Virtues Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, becauſe that as gates are ſupported by hinges, ſo is the honeſtie and ſanctitie of all morall life by theſe Cardinall virtues.</p>
            <p>But heere the opinion of <hi>Menedemus, Ariſton,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17163:25"/> others, who aboliſhing all pluralitie and difference of Virtues, ſuppoſe there is but one onely Virtue, which is Prudence, and the ſame is knowne by divers names. For, conſider wee what ought to bee done, or not done, then it carrieth the name Prudence. Conſider we what is due in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce, it hath the name of Juſtice. What in ſuffering, then For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; and when we governe our luſts and affections, then we call it Temperance. For as fire, though it worke upon divers ſubjects, yet it is one and the ſelfe ſame fire; or as a knife, though it cut now one thing, now another, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not it's property: no more doth a good man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>tanquam ipſa virtus,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17163:26"/> though hee bee converſant in divers matters, and ſundry affaires. True it is, no one Virtue can bee without another.<note place="margin">D. Ambr.</note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, when they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, then are they joyned, but disjoyntly, no way can they be perfect. Becauſe Prudence cannot be true, which is not juſt, valiant and temperate; nor Temperance perfect, which is not pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, valiant and juſt; Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Greg.</note> 
               <hi>Iſtae virtutes ita in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro ſunt, ut una aliam non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedat, magna quippe eſt Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, ſed, ſi minùs eſt à vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatibus temperans, minùs in periculis fortis, minùs in operationibus juſta, profectò minùs eſt Prudens. Magna eſt Temperantia, ſed, ſi minùs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17163:26"/> undè ſe temperat, ſi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa ſustinere per fortitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem minùs valet, atque in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more animum deijcit, ſi per praeceptionem ſuam aliquandò ad injuſtitiae opera prorumpit, minùs eſt temperans. Magna eſt Fortitudo ſed ſi minùs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligit, quae bona cuſtodiat, quibus malis reſistat, ſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus à voluptatis appetitu ſe temperat, Sed vincitur dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatione; ſi Iuſtitiae opera mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs tenet, atque aliquandò ad injuſtitiae opera dominatione ſuperatur, minùs eſt fortis. Magna eſt juſtitia, ſed ſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs quàm debet, inter juſta &amp; injuſta opera diſcernit, ſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs cor a mundi delectatione temperat, ſi minùs ſe contra adverſa confortat, minùs eſt juſta. Menſuretur ergo perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum fidelium vita per qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drum,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17163:27"/> &amp; tantum habeat ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualis atrij latus unum, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm latera ſingula, quia unuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque tantùm prudens eſt, quantùm temperans; &amp; juſtus tantùm, quantùm prudens, temperans &amp; fortis fuerit.</hi> And to this purpoſe ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if I have runne too long in Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drature, his Elegance invited mee to it, nor will I make him to ſpeake Engliſh, leſt I ſhould prejudice his better Dialect. The whole ſcope of what I have urged from him, is to ſhew, <hi>Concentum &amp; harmoniam,</hi> the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious concent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe virtues among themſelves, and the mutuall dependencie of each one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other, by way of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17163:27"/> and communion, till they all (as it were) conſpire and meet in one and the ſame u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which unity <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> conceiteth,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> when hee ſayeth Prudence alone, and by it ſelfe is no way perfect, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſaying, Hee that is prudent, is conſtant, and hee that is conſtant, is without moleſtation, and he that is without moleſtation, is without ſorrow, hee that is without ſorrow is bleſſed; therefore a Prudent man is a bleſſed man, and Prudence is ſufficient for a bleſſed life. Theſe virtues are ſo conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with a certaine mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall copulation, as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our body, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in amiable concord as muſicall harmony, that I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17163:28"/> may ſay, this is that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold order of rings, which <hi>Plato</hi> writeth to be drawen out of the Loadſtone,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> and hence it may bee, that they are tearmed, <hi>Matres virtutum, connexae ſunt ſibi virtutes &amp; coordinatae, ita ut, qui unam habet, habeat omnes. Prima ratio eſt largitas Dei dantis: quia non dat unam ſine aliâ. Secunda ratio eſt: quia ſicut unum membrum indiget alio, ſic eſt in virtutibus. Tertia ratio eſt, quia ſicut in Citharâ, ſi defuerit una chor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, non erit harmonia perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta: ita nec in animâ erit ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualis melodia, niſi adſint omnes virtutes. Quarta ratio eſt, quia contra ſingula vitia ſunt aliquae virtutes, unde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet omnes virtutes habere, ut omnia vitia impugnentur:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17163:28"/> nam ſicut miles mundi non eſt expeditus, niſi omnia ſua ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma habeat: ita nec Miles Chriſti, ſi aliqua virtus ſibi defuerit. Quinta ratio est, quia ſicut Stellae &amp; Planetae ſemper ſunt in ſphaeris ſuis: ita virtutes in animâ eſſe debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Sexta ratio eſt, quia ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt ſicut vas auri ſolidum, ornatum lapide precioſo, id eſt virtutibus. Septima ratio eſt, quia anima eſt ſicut hortus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis, cui non deeſt decor ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus floris, vel arboris. Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va, quia anima eſt ſicut A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheca, cui deeſſe non debet alicujus radicis vel pigmenti Medicina.</hi> Theſe vertues are ſo knit together by conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion and coordination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath one, hath all, ſaith <hi>Iohannes de Combis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. d. Comb.</note> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17163:29"/> addes the eight following reaſons, or at leaſt, Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the ſame. The firſt reaſon is, The bountie of God the giver, becauſe hee doth not give the one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other. The ſecond reaſon is, becauſe as in the ſtate of the Body, one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber needeth another: ſo is it in the dependencie of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. The third reaſon is, becauſe as in a Harpe, if one ſtring be wanting, there will not bee a perfect harmonie: ſo neither will there bee a Spirituall melodie in the ſoule, unleſſe all Virtues are preſent. The fourth reaſon is, becauſe againſt ſeverall vices, there are ſeverall Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: wherefore it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to have all Virtues, that they may reſiſt all vices: for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17163:29"/> as the Souldier of the world is not skilfull unleſſe he have all his weapons: ſo neither the Souldier of Chriſt, if he want any Virtue. The fifth reaſon is, becauſe as Starres and Planets ever are in their Sphaeres; ſo virtues ought to bee in the ſoule. The ſixt reaſon is, becauſe the ſoule is (as it were) a ſound veſſell of gold, beautified with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, that is, with Virtues. The ſeventh reaſon is, becauſe the ſoule is (as it were) a fruitfull Garden, wherein the comelineſſe of any tree or flower ought not to bee abſent. Eightly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſoule is, as it were, an Apothecaries ſhop, where there ought no herbe or rootes fit for medicine to be deficient.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17163:30"/>
            <p>Now that there are but foure Cardinal Virtues, <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> hath done mee the office to prove it;<note place="margin">Tullie.</note> becauſe Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie (ſaith hee) ſtands upon foure parts; One of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, another of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, the third of Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, the fourth of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Knowledge belongs to Prudence, Community to Juſtice, Magnanimity to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Moderation to Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance. Theſe foure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Beda,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda.</note> ſeeme to bee againſt Ignorance, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Infirmitie, and Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence. There are foure Cardinal Virtues (ſaith <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas</hi>) whereof Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence belongs to Reaſon,<note place="margin">Tho. Aquin.</note> Juſtice to Will, Temperance to Appetite, and Fortitude to Anger; and each hath his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17163:30"/> reference, <hi>peculiari quadam ratione,</hi> after a certaine pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner; thus he argues: Every morall Virtue either belongs to Reaſon, or to Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite; if unto Reaſon, it is Prudence; if unto Appetite, it doth either encline to an others, or to our own good; if to an others, it is Juſtice; if to our owne, it appeares either in brideling our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, which is Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or our Anger, which is Fortitude. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Aug. D. Greg. D. Ambr.</note> 
               <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe: Quatuor Paradiſi fluminibus totam ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram interſecantibus compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant has quatuor virtutes, quae uberrimis fluentis honeſtarum rerum vitam noſtram irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant.</hi> If this ſuffice not, five arrowes may be drawne out
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17163:31"/> of the quiver of holy Writ; the firſt, from the foure Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Paradiſe: The foure Rivers water Paradiſe; ſo by theſe foure Virtues the heart is watered, till it bee made fruitfull, and is alſo tempered from the heat of carnall deſires. The ſecond, from the foure colours, with which the hangings of the Tabernacle were graced, which ſignifie theſe foure Virtues, in which the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts. The Hyacinthian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Prudence, being of an a riall or celeſtiall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, whereby wee imitate God and Angels. The Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xie, having whiteneſſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaines to Temperance, becauſe it makes <hi>Candidam &amp; mundam animam.</hi> The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17163:31"/> Purple, to Fortitude, which is prepared <hi>Sanguinem pro Chriſto fundere.</hi> The Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, to Juſtice, <hi>propter zelum ipſius.</hi> The third, from the foure ingredients wherwith the Oyntment was made, which annointed the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, the Veſſels and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters thereof. The Myrrhe belongs to Prudence, the Cinnamon to Humilitie, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is altogether Juſtice, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in <hi>Matth.</hi> For thus it becommeth all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, that is, perfect Humilitie. Caſſia, which growes in waters, to Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which is nouriſhed in the waters of knowledge. Calamus, that odoriferous tree, to Fortitude. Theſe foure (the Oyle of divine love being added) make that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17163:32"/> moſt ſweet ſmelling ſavour of a good name, according to that of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, A good name is better than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious oyntment.</hi> The fourth from <hi>Elias</hi> his Chariot, the foure Virtues being (as it were) the foure wheeles in that fiery Chariot, by which the friends of God are taken up on high. The fifth, from the figures of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> foure Creatures, the Eagle, the Calfe, the Lyon, the Man. In the Eagle is figured Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whoſe property it is, to watch in diſcerning things: In the Calfe temperance, the Calfe being ordained for Holy Sacrifice in the Law; in the Lyon Fortitude, and in the man Juſtice, which is the bond of humane ſociety.<note place="margin">Bellarm.</note> Nor is Cardinall <hi>Bellarmines</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17163:32"/> muſicall compariſon altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther untuneable, who, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the ninety eighth Pſalme, applies the foure Inſtruments therein mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to the foure Cardinall Virtues. For ſaith hee, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thara Prudentiae ſimilis eſt, pſalterium Iuſtitiae, tuba du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilis Fortitudini, tuba cornea Temperantiae. Cithara varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rüm chordarum ſonos miſcens, unum dulcem concentum effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit: Sic Prudentia, varias circumſtantias operis boni con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungens, perfectum opus red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Pſalterium decem chordis inſtructum decalogum nobis repreſentat, id eſt, omnia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta Iuſtitiae. Tuba ductilis malleorum ictibus extenditur, &amp; formatur, ut ſonum ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimum edat; Sic Fortitudo, tribulationes, &amp; anguſtias pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientèr
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17163:33"/> ferendo, ita extendit &amp; perficit hominem dei, ut ſuavem ſonum edat: Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Temperantia quaſi durum cornu carnem mollem exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, &amp; ſuperans, id eſt, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus caſtigans jejunijs, atque vigilijs, &amp; in ſervitutem Spiritus redigens, tubam Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualem efficit.</hi> Hee apples the Harpe to Prudence, the Pſalterie to Iuſtice, the Trumpet to Fortitude, the Cornet to Temperance. For as the Harpe ſending out the ſound of divers ſtrings, makes one melodious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; So Prudence joyning together divers circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of well-doing, makes up the perfection of good workes. The Pſalterie ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ten ſtrings, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17163:33"/> that is, all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Divine and Morall Iuſtice. The Trumpet, as it is extended forth, and faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſtrokes of the hammer, that it might give a ſweet ſound, ſo Fortitude bearing patiently tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and troubles enlargeth and perfects the man of God in ſuch manner, that hee ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a perfect ſound to all hearers. Finally, as the Cornet is made of hard horne, that growes forth, and overtops the fleſh; ſo Temperance, as if it were of a horniſh compoſure, is too hard for the fleſh, by keeping under the body with faſtings and watchings, till it bring it in obedience, and make a ſpirituall harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie betweene the fleſh and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17163:34"/> the ſpirit. Neither will I forget that luckie obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Proſper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proſp.</note> who writing of the foure Cardinall Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, hath it thus: <hi>Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les quatuor eſſe virtutes, non ſolum Philoſophi ſentiunt ſed etiam noſtri conſentiunt, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem totus orbis Oriente, &amp; Occidente, Aquilone, &amp; Merid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Et ipſe Adam vel generale nomen, quod dicitur homo, quatuor in literis: Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus quoque quatuor elementis, &amp; anima ipſius quatuor affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionibus explicatur; ideò vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes iſtas, quae tantam perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem in numero habent, ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitè conſiderare debemus, quia nihil perfectionis uſpiàm ſit, quod in iſtis virtutibus non ſit.</hi> That there are foure principall Virtues is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, not onely of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17163:34"/> but of us Divines alſo (which the Father manifeſts thus:) The whole world is expreſſed within the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South. And <hi>Adam</hi> himſelfe, as alſo his generall name, which is <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> is expreſſed in foure let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. His body likewiſe by foure Elements, and his ſoule by foure Affections. Therefore wee ought dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to conſider of theſe Virtues, which have in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſo great perfection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe indeed no perfection is any where to be found, which is not found in theſe Virtues. Now to quarter out the Quaternion with Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D Bern. Hugo de S. Victore.</note> and <hi>Hugo de ſancto victore; Iuſtitia quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Prudentia invenit, Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17163:35"/> vindicat, &amp; Temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia poſſidet. Prudentia docet &amp; informat, Iuſtitia ornat, &amp; conſummat, Fortitudo retinet &amp; roborat, Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perantia mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur &amp; diſcernit.</hi> Prudence inſtructs, Iuſtice beautifies, Fortitude ſtrengthens, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance moderates. Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>in elegendis,</hi> Iuſtice <hi>in diſtribuendis,</hi> Temperance <hi>in utendis,</hi> Fortitude <hi>in tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randis.</hi> And this is that foure-fold linke, that chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth man to eternity. The laſt invites me on the left hand, <hi>Non ſuccumbere in adverſis,</hi> the third on the right hand, <hi>Non elevari in Proſperis:</hi> the ſecond, a <hi>Poſteriori,</hi> to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>de Praeteritis,</hi> and now my inſuing Prudence gives me a Caveat <hi>defuturis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though it is held prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17163:35"/> in the Schooles, to divide before we define, yet let us know from whom, to whom, and then to my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, What this Virtue is,<note place="margin">Chryſip.</note> becauſe as <hi>Chryſippus</hi> tells me, each hath a peculiar qualitie, and therefore needeth a ſeverall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17163:36"/>
            <head>The Originall of all virtue, whence it ſprings. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the <hi>à Quo,</hi> whence Virtue is derived, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſſe multis modis oſtendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, hoc enim fides recta teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſacra ſcriptura loquitur, comparatio rerum ad ipſum idipſum indicat, ſancti praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, creaturae clamant, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio naturalis dictat.</hi> And if all theſe proofes were ſilent, yet the heathens would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a Divinitie in its O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall,<note place="margin">Plat.</note> 
               <hi>Totius rerum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, origo &amp; cauſa deus eſt;</hi> God is the cauſe and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all things, ſaith <hi>Plato,</hi> the Philoſophicall Divine.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17163:36"/> 
               <hi>Socrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soc.</note> no leſſe a Divine Philoſopher, held, that there was but one God, and that was <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega: Deus in unâ exiſtentiâ omnia ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet;</hi> God in one exiſtence hath all things,<note place="margin">Dio.</note> (ſayd <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius) Eſſe omnium eſt ipſa divinitas, omne quod vides, &amp; quod non vides,</hi> the very being of all things, whether of things viſible or invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible is the Godhead it ſelfe. And <hi>Plato</hi> affirmes,<note place="margin">Pla.</note> that vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is given us from God, and not from men. <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius Triſmegiſtus</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Triſ.</note> that God is, <hi>Principium uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſorum,</hi> the originall of the Vniverſe.<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>Quod omnes antiquide-creverunt, quaſi quoddam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum principium, ipſumque infinitum;</hi> That all antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17163:37"/> have decreed as it were, a certaine beginning of things, &amp; the ſame infinit. For God, whoſoever he be (ſaith <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi>) and in what place ſoever reſident,<note place="margin">Plin.</note> is all Science, all Light, all Life, all Soule, and all of himſelfe. As Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers conjecture, ſo the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church with all modern Divines juſtifie, that there is a Coeleſtiall power from w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> al goodnes flowes. Among the reſt ſaith <hi>Raimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Sabundus</hi> by way of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude: <hi>Sicut homo non dedit inferiori rei eſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sab.</note> 
               <hi>ita neque ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> intelligere, ergo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem manus omnia fecit, idem dominus, idem artifex omnia ordinavit, proportionavit, &amp; limitavit;</hi> Eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a man hath not given power to any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior thing, either to live, or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17163:37"/> to perceive: ſo neither doth man give unto himſelf, either to be, either to live, either to perceive, or to underſtand; therfore the ſame hand hath made all things, the ſame Lord, the ſame builder, hath ordained, proportioned, and limited all things. Againe, <hi>Deus eſt author &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditor om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> God is the author and founder of all things. If of all things, then of all goodneſſe. <hi>Omnia bona, quae in hoc ſeculo habemus, per gratiam dei habemus;</hi> All the goods,<note place="margin">Bern.</note> which wee have in this world (ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) wee have by the grace of God. Certainely hee is the beginning of all things; the Idea and Patterne of all Good. He is that Almighty which wanteth beginning
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17163:38"/> and ending, which, being made of none, hath by his power created all things, and therefore by ſome he is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Well, both becauſe he hath all good things from himſelfe, and alſo, for that hee doth communicate all good things from thence unto his creatures, without any hinderance to himſelfe. <hi>Superior verò, ratione, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, virtute, ſapientiâ, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Deus eſt, ſub quo volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tariè vel invitè curvantur omnes, qui regunt, vel regere cupiunt orbem. Quorum leges, velut aranearum telae ſunt, Si divinis legibus adverſantur: imò (ut arctiùs aſtringam) ſi non obſequuntur;</hi> God is, verely ſuperior to all, in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Authority, Virtue, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience, under whom volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17163:38"/> or againſt their will, all are curbed, who governe, or deſire to governe the world, whoſe lawes are as the webs of Spiders, if they but croſſe divine lawes: yea (that I may ſpeake more cloſely) if they accord not with them (if <hi>Simon de Caſsia</hi> erre not.) Sir <hi>Thomas Elliot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sim. de Caſſ. Ell.</note> in his Dialogue betweene <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> urgeth, That Philoſophers ſpake too little of God, ſince they did not conclude, that all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe proceeded from him, and that hee was the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and Principall thereof. For although they did, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all, acknowledge a dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet the Philoſophers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers opinions have juſtified that old Proverbe: <hi>Quot homines tot ſententiae.</hi> To
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17163:39"/> which purpoſe <hi>Lactantius</hi> writes very pithily,<note place="margin">Lactan.</note> 
               <hi>Horum omnium ſententia, quamvis ſit incerta,, eodem tamen ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat, ut providentiam unam eſſe conſentiunt: ſive enim natura, ſive aether, ſive ratio, ſive mens, ſive fatalis neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ſive divina lex, idem eſt, quod a nobis dicitur Deus;</hi> All theſe opinions, though uncertaine, come to this, that they agree upon one provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whether the ſame be Nature, or Light, or Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or Deſtiny, or divine Ordinance, and that it is the ſame, which is called of us God. <hi>Dicitur Dominus quaſi dans munus; &amp; nota, quod dicitur domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus propter triplex munus:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17163:39"/>Propter
<list>
                     <item> terrae fertilitatem,</item>
                     <item>aëris claritatem,</item>
                     <item>temporis tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liltatem.</item>
                  </list>
               </hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primum munus datur divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitùs propter noſtram ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtationem;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secundum propter actionem;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertium propter contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee is called the Lord,<note place="margin">Bonaven.</note> (ſaith <hi>Bonaventure</hi>) becauſe (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth) he loadeth us with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits; and note, that hee is called the Lord for a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold benefit given us: for the fertilitie of Earth, the clearneſſe of light, and the tranquility of time. The firſt gift is given us from above for our ſuſtentation; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17163:40"/> for our action; the third, for our contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Omnes Corporis &amp; animi vires, omnia membra noſtra, Oculi, Aures, Lingua, Manus, Pedes, Affectus, &amp; quicquid modò in nobis, ejus dilectioni, et obſequio totum intrà et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà mancipetur, et ſyncerè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecretur.</hi> All the ſtrength of Body &amp; Mind; all our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Eyes, Eares, Tongue, Hands, Affections, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in us either intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall or extrinſecall, ought to obey, and ſyncerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate themſelves to his wil and pleaſure (ſaith <hi>Theodori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod.</note>) Volumes might bee written to this purpoſe, yet all would bee but ſo many <hi>Items</hi> to make up one ſum, which are included in theſe words of <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clem. Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xand.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17163:40"/> which ſerve my turne to conclude this poynt, <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus unum Patrem, &amp; Fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, unà cum Spiritu ſancto, qui unus est omnia, in quo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, per quem omnia, qui eſt undequá<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bonus, undequáque pulcher, undequáque ſapiens, undequáque juſtus, cui gloria nunc eſt, &amp; in ſecula.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17163:41"/>
            <head>The true Subject of Virtue, to whom it properly belongs. <hi>CAP. III.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow let us determine the <hi>Quibus,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of Virtues ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject aright: for here ſome ſcruple may ariſe from the different opinion of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers and Divines: For, (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) this one Province belongs to a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
               <hi>Vt rectè proſpiciat.</hi> Therefore certaine beaſts may bee ſaid to be prudent, to wit, all thoſe that ſeeme to bee endued with an eagre deſire of providing thoſe things, which doe belong to the defending of their life, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17163:41"/> which purpoſe ſaith one:
<q>
                  <l>Nor are theſe creatures to bee thought to bee</l>
                  <l>Quite void of th'intellectuall facultie;</l>
                  <l>But that they can diſcerne and underſtand</l>
                  <l>The language ſpoken in their native land,</l>
                  <l>And might diſcourſe, if to ſo ſtrange a wit,</l>
                  <l>Nature had lent them but due organs fit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucan</hi> ſaith, It is reported, that Elephants come out of the Rabathaean woods,<note place="margin">Lucan.</note> and in a flood neere adjoyning waſh themſelves, (as if to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie) then proſtrating fall downe, &amp; adore the Moone, and with joy returne unto the woods againe.</p>
            <p>What if I ſhould compare
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17163:42"/> this Story of the Elephants with that of <hi>Plinie?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin.</note> (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you would judge theſe beaſts wiſer than ſome men) who in his naturall Hiſtorie thus rebukes men for their pluralitie of gods; to beleeve that there bee gods innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and thoſe according to mens virtues or vices, to wit, Charitie, Concord, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Hope, Honour, Clemencie, Faith, or (as <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus</hi> was of opinion) that there were two Gods onely, Puniſhment, and Reward, makes mens idleneſſe the greater. Hereupon it is (ſaith he) that ſundry Nations have gods named according to their devotion; nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hurts unto men have been reckoned gods, which ſuperſtition hath cauſed a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17163:42"/> Chappell to bee dedicated to the Feaver in the mount <hi>Palatium,</hi> even by publike order from the State; Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe an altar to <hi>Orbona,</hi> neere the temple of <hi>Lares;</hi> Beſides an other erected to bad For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in <hi>Eſquiliae,</hi> which would argue, that there were more gods in heaven, than men on earth.</p>
            <p>And what of thoſe, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count beaſts, and ſome filthy things for their gods. If all the ridiculous idolatrie men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the olde Scripture were let ſlip,<note place="margin">Godw.</note> yet <hi>Godwin</hi> in his Antiquities will tell us, that at the laſt, inferiour creatures were canonized for gods, in way of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for benefits received from them; For which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, theſe, as the Winds, the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17163:43"/> Ayre, the Earth, the Fruits of the earth, became deified. At laſt, well deſerving men, nay Crocodiles, Serpents, Rats, Cats, Dogs, Garlike, and Onions were reputed gods.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lactan.</note>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> writing of the varietie of the Romane, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian, and Lacedemonian gods, not only blames them, becauſe they did, <hi>Deos ſibi ex eventis fingere,</hi> feign gods to themſelves from each ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall accident, according to their owne imaginations, but falleth fowler on them in theſe words, <hi>Quid, qui lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem colunt informem atque rudem?</hi> What of thoſe, that worſhip a rude and unbeau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified ſtone? And in another place he thus explaines him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Quid de ijs dicam, qui
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17163:43"/> colunt talia, niſi ipſos potiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum lapides, ac ſripites eſſe?</hi> What ſhall I ſay of thoſe that worſhip ſenſleſſe ſtocks and ſtones, unleſſe they, in the higheſt degree, were ſtockes and ſtones? Is it not then ſafer to live <hi>more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> after the manner of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage beaſts, then to bee the authors of ſuch idolatry. But the Scripture tells us, wee muſt not expect grapes of thornes, nor figs from thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. It is no wonder then, that theſe things bee, ſince they proceed from Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Quorum religio cum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus congruit.</hi> Some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps admire theſe Stories, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blame mee for urging them; but all muſt like that ingenious tranſlation of <hi>May</hi> on <hi>Lucan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">May.</note> who concerning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17163:44"/> that of the Elephants, thus writes;
<q>
                  <l>Should this bee true of Elephants, much more</l>
                  <l>Wiſe in Religion are theſe beaſts then men.</l>
                  <l>But, if this a Fiction bee, why then</l>
                  <l>Did mens Invention faigne them to bee</l>
                  <l>Wiſer then are themſelves in pietie?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Though beaſts in the act of generation will accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with none other, but ſuch as bee of their owne proper kind, (though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous in proportion, and ſhape) as Wolves and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtives, Hares and Conies, &amp;c. Though the Bee ſuffer not another, that is not of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17163:44"/> the ſame kind, to enter into her Hive, though dogges at the voice of the Faulconer, or Huntſman, ſeeme to joy, as if they ſhould enjoy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime; yet this is not pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Doth the horſe know that he is a horſe, or, that he is a beaſt, and thou a man? or the Bee when her hive is broken, whether it be a man, or a beaſt that takes her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie combes, and puts her out of her lodging? or doth the Dogge (which of all beaſts is mans chiefe atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant) know, whether thou art a man, or a beaſt? no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely. What thinke you of your <hi>Fauni,</hi> your <hi>Satyri,</hi> your <hi>Hippocentauri,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other beaſts, ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the viſage, others the whole figure of mans body,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17163:45"/> are theſe endued with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? no; for they want a reaſonable ſoule, which is the ſole difference betweene man and beaſt, which ſoule makes man prudent and wiſe unto ſalvation: doe they know that they are ſuch beaſts? or, that they doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble man? no verely: onely man knowes that hee is man, and every beaſt in his ſeverall kind, according to that of <hi>Socrates;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat.</note> Wiſedome is in man, and not in a beaſt, and all wiſedome is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in him in this word, <hi>[Noſce teipſum.]</hi> Though beaſts obſerve order, yet, I can no way conceive, that to bee otherwiſe, then an imagination engendred by cuſtome. For that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which is in beaſts, is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17163:45"/> by a naturall influence, if you adde thereunto their ſenſes. In this I refer you to <hi>Piccolomineus</hi> his judgment,<note place="margin">Piccol.</note> who ſaith, that Prudence is two-fold, one divine, the other proper to mortality; divine prudence is eminent, ſeparated from all indaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and imperfection, which is given to God, <hi>Et ſeparatis mentibus.</hi> The Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Mortality is two-fold, either naturall, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane: that which is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, is not a true Prudence, but a ſhaddow thereof: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as by nature, and the inſtinct of nature, beaſts doe chooſe thoſe things which alſo wiſe men doe. So Ants gather their grane, Bees make their combes, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their King, and Birds for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17163:46"/> variety of time change their places. Now humane Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is alſo two-fold, either <hi>in ſpe &amp; ſemine,</hi> which are children, when by nature they ſhew themſelves facile to Prudence, and yeeld a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hope thereof: or <hi>in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu &amp; formâ,</hi> which is uſed for callidity or craft, ſuch are Devils, ſubtill Machevilians, and thoſe which are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called the prudent or wiſe men of this world, but the true humane pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, properly taken, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with morall virtue, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king meanes to attaine unto honeſty, is my enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which bids me <hi>Quaere</hi> for'd <hi>Quid eſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17163:46"/>
            <head>The Definition of Prudence, the firſt of the foure Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Virtues. <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Stoicks ſay, that it is <hi>Scientia bonorum, malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; mediorum. Speuſip pus</hi> is of opinion,<note place="margin">Spen.</note> that it is onely <hi>Scientia bonorum &amp; malorum.</hi> Whereby wee judge, what is to be done, and what not: and ſo ſaith <hi>Cicero. Plotinus</hi> informes us,<note place="margin">Plot.</note> that Prudence is an underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, declining inferiour things, and directing the mind to ſupernall. But the <hi>Genus</hi> of Prudence is found in none of theſe definitions, according to <hi>Piccolomineus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pieco.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17163:47"/> for <hi>eligere divina &amp; negligere mortalia,</hi> is not the office of Prudence, as it is univerſall, but as it is heroicall; neither is <hi>Prudentia, Scientia et Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> according to <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eurip.</note> 
               <hi>Euripides</hi> and others ſay that it is <hi>Habitus mentis,</hi> whereby every one doth ſeeke that which is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to himſelfe, which alſo is not to bee approved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the principall gift of Prudence, is to ſeek out that, which is moſt good for the publike, not our owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per good, the end whereof is rather to bee accounted honeſt then profitable: but <hi>Audi Philoſophum,</hi> Prudence is a habit directing to doe thoſe things with true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which are good to man; whereupon ſaith one, the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17163:47"/> habite is the <hi>Genus,</hi> and the forme thereof, it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (with true reaſon) by which is ſhewed that Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, doth belong to Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and to that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of Vnderſtanding, which is called <hi>Rationatrix,</hi> according to that in <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> thoſe are prudent,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> who can rightly take Councell in thoſe things, which are good and profitable to themſelves, not which is <hi>ad valetudinem aut vires,</hi> but altogether to reaſon of our well living: Againe hee termes it a virtue of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, by which wee may well conſult of Good and Evill things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto Felicitie.<note place="margin">Gol.</note> 
               <hi>Gollius</hi> cloſeth with him, and thus he ſayeth: <hi>Prudentia eſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17163:48"/> mentis ſecundum veram rationem conſultandi, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendi ea, quae homini in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſâ vitâ ſunt bona vel ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. Prudens eſt is, qui poteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè conſultare de ijs, quae ipſi, vel alijs ſunt bona, &amp; utilia, non ex parte ſolùm aliquâ, ſed ad totam benè vivendi ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem;</hi> Prudence is a habite of the underſtanding, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true reaſon of conſulting, and doing thoſe things which are good, or evill, during mans life. He is Prudent, who can well conſult concerning thoſe things, which are good, and profitable for himſelfe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not alone for ſome particular part, but for the whole courſe of well living. <hi>Macrobius</hi> confeſſeth,<note place="margin">Macr.</note> That it is a Virtue directing all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17163:48"/> things to the rule of reaſon, which doth thinke and doe nothing, beſides what is right and laudable. And <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> will tell us,<note place="margin">Thom.</note> That true and perfect Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is, wherby wee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, judge, and obey what things belong <hi>Ad finem bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum,</hi> to the end of all good things in humane converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As for the preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, I approve of <hi>Gregories</hi> opinion among Divines, and <hi>Platoes</hi> among Philoſophers, The firſt inſtructs us, That Prudence, <hi>inter reliquas Principem locum obtinet, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet alias virtutes, niſi, quae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, Prudenter agant, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes eſſe neutiquàm poſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Greg.</note> Amongſt other virtues, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence obtaines the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, and teacheth the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17163:49"/> reſt, that unleſſe, what things they doe, they doe wiſely, they cannot be vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. And <hi>Plato, Virtutes omnes ad Prudentiam revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plat.</note> 
               <hi>illaſque ſine hujus praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, quaſi Daedali ſtatuas ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutas, fugaces, &amp; inſtabiles eſſe aiebat. Plato</hi> reduced all virtues unto Prudence, and affirmed that thoſe, without its ayde, are but, as it were, the ſtatues of <hi>Daedalus,</hi> weakened, fading, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable. Well then hath <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowne</hi> termed it,<note place="margin">Char.</note> The ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent, and guide of all other virtues; <hi>Aurigam vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum,</hi> without which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is good; The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and choice of thoſe things, which wee deſire or fly, The juſt eſtimation and triall of things, the eye, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17163:49"/> ſeeth all, directeth and ordaineth all. Better is that of <hi>Tully</hi> in his Tuſculanes:<note place="margin">Tul.</note> 
               <hi>Non poteſt eſſe jucunda vita, à quâ abeſt Prudentia:</hi> But beſt of all, ſayeth <hi>Iambli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iamb.</note> after a long commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this virtue: <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritò Dei ſimiles facit ſui poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſores Prudentia.</hi> I need not incite any to the deſire ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for it is <hi>Gratuita virtus</hi> (as <hi>Peraldus</hi> noteth) as it is <hi>Gratuita,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Per.</note> ſo ought it to be <hi>Amabilis,</hi> every way as much to be beloved, as it is freely beſtowed on us.<note place="margin">Bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v.</note> 
               <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> urgeth foure Reaſons, wherefore it is <hi>Amabilis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is <hi>Luminoſa in quantum temporum diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Fructuoſa in quantum futurorum proviſiva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17163:50"/>3. <hi>Studioſa in quantum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritorum recordativa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Operoſa in quantum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium ordinativa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now you have read ſo many Definitions, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, take your choice; yet this of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> I muſt approve of,<note place="margin">D. Aug.</note> which is, <hi>Scire quid anima debet facere.</hi> And heere a diviſion would be demanded; yet before I come to it, a word or two of the difference betweene <hi>Prudentia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sapientia.</hi> True it is, in holy Writ, the words are promiſcuouſly handled; An inſtance or two of the congruitie of the wordes. <hi>Prudentia carnis mors eſt, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia autem Spiritus vita, &amp; pax; quoniam ſapientia carnis inimica eſt Deo;</hi> The wiſedome of the fleſh is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17163:50"/> death, but the wiſedome of the ſpirit is life, and peace; becauſe the wiſedome of the fleſh is enmity againſt God. <hi>Qui ſapiens eſt corde, appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur Prudens:</hi> The wiſe in heart ſhall be called Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. And againe, <hi>Os meum loquitur ſapientiam, &amp; medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio cordis mei prudentiam,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt.<note place="margin">Damaſ.</note> 
               <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene</hi> dividing the Rationall ſoule into two parts, into that, which is Active, and into that, which is Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative, ſayeth, that the Contemplative belongs to Sapience, the Active to Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. But how will this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
               <hi>Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, in ipſis artibus, ijs tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buere ſolemus, qui in quâque arte excellunt maximè, ut Phydiam ſapientem lapidum
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17163:51"/> ſculptorem, &amp; Polycletum ſtatuarium ſapientem nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus;</hi> Wee are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſaith hee, to attribute Sapience to thoſe, which doe in the higheſt degree excell in any kinde of Art, As wee call <hi>Phydias</hi> a wiſe Carver of Stones, <hi>Polycletus</hi> a wiſe maker of Images, which name of Sapience ſignifies no other thing, than the virtue or excellencie of Art; and in another place, <hi>Quod ſapientis nomine appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur, quod verò prudentis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine dicitur, aliud atque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud:</hi> What is called by the name of a Sapientiall man, is one thing, what of a Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is another thing: And here hee gives another Example; <hi>Anaxagoram, Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letem, cateroſque tales ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17163:51"/> nominamus, prudentes non itèm:</hi> We call <hi>Anaxagoras, Thales,</hi> and ſuch men wiſe, but not prudent. His reaſon followes, becauſe they doe not perceive, but are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of thoſe things, which are profitable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Sapientia eſt de rebus humanis &amp; divinis cognitio, Prudentia de moribus;</hi> Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (ſaith <hi>Tullie</hi>) is a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of divine and humane things,<note place="margin">Tul.</note> Prudence appertains unto manners. <hi>Eſt in ratione quiddam, ad ſuperna &amp; coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia incendens, &amp; id dicitur Sapientia, &amp; eſt quiddam ad tranſitoria, &amp; caduca reſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, &amp; id vocatur Prudentia: haec duo ex ratione ſunt, &amp; in ratione conſiſtunt; &amp; dividit ſe ratio in duo, ſcilicet, in ſurſùm, &amp; deorſùm; ſurſùm
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17163:52"/> in Sapientiam, &amp; deorſùm in Prudentiam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Aug.</note> There is in Reaſon (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) a certaine thing bending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſupernal, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and that is called Sapience: there is a certaine thing reſpecting ttanſitorie and fleeting things, and this is called Prudence: Theſe two are from Reaſon, and conſiſt in Reaſon, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon divideth it ſelfe into two, to wit, upward, and downward; upward into Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience, downward into Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. There hee gives a ſimilitude, <hi>Quaſi in virum &amp; mulierem, ut vir ſit ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, et regat; mulier inferior, &amp; regatur:</hi> As it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a man and a woman; the man being ſuperior, in the active voyce governes,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17163:52"/> the woman inferior, in the paſſive, is governed: ſo that I might liken Sapience, and Prudence to thoſe two great and heavenly Lights, the Sunne, and the Moone; for as the Moone receives her ſplendour from the Sunne; ſo Prudence its from Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and as the Moone rules the night, and the Sunne the day; ſo Prudence rules this, Morall Sapience the divine life. And now deſcend wee in the next place to a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:17163:53"/>
            <head>The Diviſion, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Branches of Prudence. <hi>CAP. V.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Prudence, I finde too too much diviſion in opinions. <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> brancheth it into more parts,<note place="margin">Thom.</note> than any other mention, to wit, <hi>Memoria Intelligentia, Docilitas, Soler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Ratio, Providentia, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectio &amp; Cautio.</hi> But theſe may be drawen into a leſſer circle,<note place="margin">Per.</note> 
               <hi>Peraldus</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the opinion of <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tul.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Sen.</note> who ſay the parts thereof, are three, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria, Intelligentia, et Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia,</hi> and ſo is the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17163:53"/> of others, no leſſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Divinitie, than they in Moralitie. Others would adde one wheele more, to make it a compleate Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, which is <hi>Aſtutia mentis;</hi> But in mine owne opinion, I conceive it to be, rather an Appendix on the three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parts, then to challenge any part thereof; and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to handle it.<note place="margin">Aug.</note> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> I believe will cleare all, (whoſe opinion <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> confirmeth) who ſpeaking of the parts of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſayeth thus: <hi>Partes ejus Memoria, Intelligentia &amp; Providentia; Memoria eſt per quam animus repetit illa quae fuerunt; Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia per quam ea perſpicit, quae ſunt, Providentia per quam futurum aliquid videtur, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequàm
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17163:54"/> eſt;</hi> The parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are Memory, Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Providence; Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is by which the minde repeates thoſe things, which were; Vnderſtanding, by which ſhee ſees thoſe things which are; Providence by which any thing to come is ſeene before it cometh; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie hath reference to things paſt, Vnderſtanding to things preſent, but hee is provident, who can appoint, from things paſt, and things preſent, that which hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall come to paſſe, ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mar.</note> And now, if my memory faile me not, I will relate what I have read <hi>de Memoriâ.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:17163:54"/>
            <head>Of Memorie, the firſt part of Prudence. <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Emoria ſumitur tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitèr: primò, pro ipſâ facultate, ceu po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ quâ recordamur; ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dò, pro recordandi actu; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, pro habitu:</hi> Memorie is taken three manner of waies (ſaith <hi>Albertus</hi>): Firſt,<note place="margin">Alb.</note> for the very facultie or power, by which we remember, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, Thirdly, for the habite; but to my definition: <hi>Memoria eſt, quâ repetit ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quae fuerunt,</hi> Memory is, by which the minde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peates what things were (ſaith <hi>Cicero)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic.</note> 
               <hi>Memoria eſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17163:55"/> vis animae accepta retinens, praeterita repetens, elapſa re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colligens;</hi> Memory is a force of the Vnderſtanding, retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things received, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating things paſt, recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting things let ſlip; Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording ſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Hugo de ſancto victore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Hug.</note> 
               <hi>Memoria eſt ad mentis intu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itum imaginaria quaedam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatio praeteritorum;</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie is a certaine imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie repreſentation of things paſt, according to the inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Memorie is the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of innumerable imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) Memoria theſaurus cognoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Per.</note> ſaith <hi>Peraldus. Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium rerum theſaurus &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos memoria eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hug.</note> ſaith <hi>Hugo.</hi> Memory is the conſort and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17163:55"/> fellow-worker of reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without it, reaſon nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can proceed to knowne things, nor retaine the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thinges knowne. <hi>Ingenium requirit incogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, memoria recondit dijudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata, ratio judicat inventa: ingenium quod invenit, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni adducit, ratio memoriae, memoria recondit:</hi> Wit (ſaith <hi>Bonaventure</hi>) ſeeketh unknowne things;<note place="margin">Bonaven.</note> Memory puts up things that be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Reaſon judges things, that be found out: what Wit findes out, it brings to Reaſon, Reaſon to Memory, Memory keepes it ſafe-guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Memory is in place of a Notary, and Secretary, and, as it were, a Regiſter Booke, in which is entred, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ordained, and decreed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17163:56"/> by Reaſon: For, as we have need of ſuch a Judge, as Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to conclude, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine finally in the Minde whatſoever may bee called into queſtion, and doubted of: ſo it is requiſite, that the Concluſion, and definitive ſentence, ſhould be regiſtred in Memory, as it were in a roll, or booke of Accompts, that it may bee alway ready and found, when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
               <hi>Memoria ſpecies om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſenſibiles judicatas, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatas, tanquam depoſitum, recondit, ac ſervat, ut eas, cum opus fuerit, exhibeat;</hi> Memory keepes and hides (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) as it were a thing depoſited, all ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpecies judged, and thought one; that ſhe may uſe them, when neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17163:56"/> 
               <hi>Sicut lux at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lores, formae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los diſcernuntur; per aures om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia genera ſonrou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: omnes odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res per aditum narium: om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſapores per oris aditum: per ſenſum autèm totius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, quid durum, quid molle, quid calidum, frigidumve, lene aut aſperum, grave ſeu leve, ſive extrinſecùs, ſive intrinſecùs corpori; haec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia recipit recolenda (cum opus eſt) &amp; retractanda gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis memoriae receſſus;</hi> As Light and all colours, and ſhapes of bodies are diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the eyes; by the eares all kindes of ſounds; all odours by the paſſage of the noſe; all taſtes by that of the mouth, and by the ſenſe of the whole body, what is hard, what ſoft,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17163:57"/> what warme or cold, gentle or ſharpe, heavy or light, either extrinſecally or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally: ſo all theſe things doth that grand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of the memory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; yea ſhee reſtores and calls them backe to minde at pleaſure:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> And here this holy Father is almoſt puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led betwixt ignorance and wonder, Adding, <hi>&amp; neſcio, qui ſecreti atque ineffabiles ejus ſinus,</hi> I know not, ſaith hee, her ſecret and unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wayes of receipt, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite is the memories ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. You may, by theſe words of <hi>Saint Auguſtine,</hi> perceive, that all ſpecies of things extrinſecally, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally belonging to the body of man, are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended within this great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17163:57"/> Memory, yet let me adviſe that none hoord up all their treaſure in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, leſt time ſhould leſſen their ſtocke. Now Memory is two-fold, as ſome would have it, one Senſitive, the other Intellective: according to this diſtinction, <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eſt iterata reſumpſio ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus apprehenſi ſenſu vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu:</hi> Memory is an ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated reſumption of ſome thing apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by Senſe or Vnderſtanding. Others well learned, thinke there is only a Senſitive memory; and good reaſon for it, it being one of the internall ſenſes, <hi>Memoria in parte ſenſitivâ ponitur, quia eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus, prout cadit ſub deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minato tempore; non enim eſt niſi praeteriti, &amp; cum non ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrahatur,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17163:58"/> niſi à ſingularibus conditionibus, non pertinet ad partem intellectivam, quae eſt univerſalium;</hi> Memory is placed in the ſenſitive part (ſaith <hi>Thomas Aqui:</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Tho.</note>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is of ſome thing, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as it chanceth in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate time; for it is not but of things paſt, and ſince it is not drawne but from ſingular and particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, it doth not belong to the Intellective part, which is of univerſalls. And <hi>Albertus</hi> ſpeakes to the ſame purpoſe.<note place="margin">Alb.</note> Others would have an Intellective memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>Memoria intellectiva ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li homini pèculiaris eſt, &amp; cuſtos &amp; conſervatrix fidiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma conceptuum &amp; imaginum, vel rerum, quarum ſpecies ſunt ab intellectu perceptae;</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:17163:58"/> The Intellective memory (ſay they) is peculiar onely to man, it is the faithfulleſt keeper of conceipts and imaginations, or of things, whoſe ſpecies are percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Vnderſtanding: But, by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, this is not Organicall. And this, I conceive, to bee that Memory, which by the Philoſopher is called <hi>Pars integralis prudentiae.</hi> Evident is the opinion of <hi>Plinie,</hi> that Dogges, Kine, Oxen,<note place="margin">Plin.</note> and Goats, &amp;c. doe dreame, <hi>Non ſomniarent bruta niſi ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berent in ſomnis, &amp;c.</hi> Brute beaſts would not dreame, unleſſe they had in their ſleepes encountering imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations kept in the inward ſenſe; which, if it hold true, what ſhall wee conceive of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17163:59"/> 
               <hi>Tullies</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Tull.</note> that <hi>Inter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem &amp; belluam hoc maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè intereſt, quod haec tantùm, quantùm movetur ſenſu, ad id ſolum, quod adeſt, quodque praeſens eſt, ſe accommodat; Paululum admodum ſentiens praeterium, vel futurum?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and beaſt this is a ſpeciall difference, that a Beaſt, onely as farre as hee is moved by ſenſe, applyeth himſelfe to that alone, which is preſent, very little perceiving a thing paſt, or to come. <hi>Alij authores ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſta indicia memoriae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, quae in brutis deprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur; certa loca, nidos, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibula, &amp; ſobolem ſuam dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcunt;</hi> Other Authours prove manifeſt ſhewes of Memory, which are diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in brute Beaſtes; they
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17163:59"/> know certaine places, their neſts, their dennes, and their off-ſprings, this opinion cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the diſtinction between <hi>Memoria</hi> and <hi>Reminiſcentia; quod illa brutis animantibus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petat ſolus verò homo remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcendi facultatem habeat;</hi> Becauſe Memory (as ſome thinke) appertaines to brute creatures, but only man hath the faculty of reminiſcence. Or better thus, <hi>Memoria dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert à reminiſcentiâ, quia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria diſcretè, &amp; diſtinctè re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertitur ad res, compone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiones diſtinctas cum ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginibus; reminiſcentia antem ſivè recordatio eſt motus quaſi interceptus, &amp; abſciſſus per ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livionem, et eſt cum collatione te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poris, &amp; loci, &amp; hujuſmodi:</hi> Memory differs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reminiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, becauſe Memory diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerningly,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17163:60"/> &amp; diſtinctly reverts unto things, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct intentions with imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, but Reminiſcence, or recordation, is a motion, as it were, intercepted, and quite loſt through oblivion, but is attained againe by collation of time, and place, and the like;<note place="margin">Ioh. de Comb</note> as <hi>Iohannes de Combis</hi> obſerves. Now <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriae eſt retinere ſpecies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligibiles, Reminiſcentiae eſt mortuas ſpecies reſuſcitare, &amp; oblivioni tradita recordari;</hi> It is Memories office, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine intelligible ſpecies, whereas Reminiſcence doth renew loſt ſpecies, and, as it were, recall to memory things delivered over to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion. To this purpoſe wee may find by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that, thoſe things which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17163:60"/> wee have heard, ſeene, or knowne, and for a little ſpace kept in memory, when once oblivion hath got the ſuperiority, wee thinke no more of, then if wee had never knowne them: nor could remember them, were there not ſome body, or evident token to put us in minde againe thereof. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tels us,<note place="margin">D. Aug. Ariſt.</note> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is in beaſts; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> confeſſeth it, but withall, That the memory that is in beaſts, is imperfect, and (in mine owne opinion) ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, that I rather thinke it a cuſtomary imagination, helpt by the externall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, then any memory at all.</p>
            <p>And now inquire wee where it is ſeated. <hi>Tres, tanquàm, ventriculi cerebri
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17163:61"/> demonſtrantur; Vnus ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ad faciem, à quo ſenſus omnis: Alter poſterior ad cervicem, à quo omnis motus: Tertius inter utrumque, in quo memoriam vigere demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrant;</hi> There are, as it were, three Ventricles of the Braine demonſtrated (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) One be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">D. Aug.</note> towards the face, from which all ſenſe; Another behinde, towards the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of the necke, from which all motion; A third between both, in which they ſhew that Memory flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. But the truth is, Divines, as well as Philoſophers, doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, That <hi>Memory</hi> is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the hinder part of the head. And thus they prove it, by a threefold reaſon. <hi>Primò, quià, laeſa illâ parte
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17163:61"/> offenditur memoria, &amp;, eo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co percuſſo, rerum caepit obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio: Secundò, quta ejus partis ſoliditas, ad id videtùr potiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimùm procurata à naturâ, ut tenacius haereant infixae ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: Poſtremò, quià, cùm recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dari volumus, quaſi naturâ nos docente, occipitium ſcalpimus, ut memorandi vim quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modò excitemus, &amp; acua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> Firſt of all, becauſe, that part being hurt, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is offended; and blowes or hurts on that place beget oblivion: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe the ſolidity of that place, eſpecially, ſeemes to be procured from nature: that the infixed ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies may take the more ſound hold: Laſt of all, becauſe, when wee would remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as it were by natures
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17163:62"/> inſtinct) wee ſcratch the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of the head, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort we may ſtirre up, or ſharpen the facultie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring. If theſe reaſons ſerve not.<note place="margin">Fr. Ac.</note> The French Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demie will tell you, That God hath aſſigned Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſeate, or lodging in the hindermoſt part of the braine; to the end, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch things, as are to be committed to it, have paſſed all the other ſenſes, they ſhould be kept there, as by a Secretary; and for this cauſe that part of the braine is moſt ſolid and firme. His reaſon you may reade at large in his Chapter of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Memory. Now there are foure things neceſſarie to whet the Memory. The Firſt is, to diſpoſe with good
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17163:62"/> order, things committed to Memorie; Then attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to meditate, and ruminate of the ſame; Afterwards to faſten the thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by ſome certaine peculiar affection of joy, or griefe; Laſt of all, when things are infixed, often to repeate and commend them to Memory. <hi>Debemus habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re memoriam trium</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure) primorum, medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, infimorum: Data ſunt enim nobis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tria
<list>
                     <item>Prima<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad guberna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum</item>
                     <item>Media ad conſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum</item>
                     <item>Infima ad ſuſtenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum.</item>
                  </list>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>As there are foure things neceſſary to ſharpen Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and three things to have in Memory: ſo there are ten
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17163:63"/> things (as <hi>Peraldus</hi> noteth) for retaining of which,<note place="margin">Per.</note> Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is eſpecially to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Firſt, the memory of benefits is to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, eſpecially, the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Creator and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: <hi>Memento Creatoris tui.</hi> Secondly, the Memorie of the Commandements of God, <hi>Et memores ſint manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum ipſius ad faciendum ea.</hi> Thirdly, the Memory of the Iuſtice, which God doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſe againſt the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his commandements, <hi>Memor eſto judicij mei, ſic e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim erit &amp; tuum.</hi> Fourthly, the Memorie of ſpirituall warre, <hi>Memento belli.</hi> Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Memorie of Divine mercie, <hi>Memoratus ſum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiae tuae, Domine.</hi> Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Memorie of the lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17163:63"/> lives of the Saints, which wee ought to imitate; <hi>Facta praecedentium patrum conſideremus.</hi> Seventhly, the Memorie of adverſity in proſperity, <hi>Memento pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis in die abundantiae.</hi> Eightly, the Memory of the Rocke, whence wee were hewed, or the Root, whence we did ſpring, <hi>Attendite ad Petram, de quâ exciſi eſtis.</hi> Ninthly, the Memorie of others wants, when wee our ſelves are in proſperity, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento mei, cum benè tibi fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Laſtly, the Memorie of private ſinnes, to grieve for them, <hi>Recogitabo tibi omnes annos, in amaritudine animae meae.</hi> The contrary to this is Oblivion, which,<note place="margin">Greg.</note> though it be (as <hi>Gregory</hi> would have it) <hi>quaedam mors:</hi> yet in ſome
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17163:64"/> things to be approved of. Firſt, the oblivion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries. Secondly, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting a good turne done to another. Thirdly, the not remembring of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in former ſinnes. And laſt of all, the non-recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of temporall things, To this purpoſe was the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> to <hi>Symmachus;</hi> to whom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to teach him the art of memory, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, hee had rather learne the art of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. A contradictory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, yet a reaſon tolerable, Meaning, that there was no defect in his memory, but that hee could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thoſe things that were requiſite to bee buried in oblivion. I might here
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17163:64"/> tell you what conſtitutions are ſubject to the beſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and that you ſhall ſeldome ſee a quicke wit, and a ſtrong memory meet, and hold: What are the cauſes of good and bad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories; That ſurfeits, and colds, according to <hi>Galen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal.</note> confound the memorie; That the matter of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the Memory, if too ſoft, will cauſe a quick entertaining, but not a good retaining; if hard, not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imprinted, but, when it is once ſetled, hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. The reaſons might evidently appeare, were they not fitter for a naturall Philoſophy Lecture, then for my Morall information. And thus have I done with memory, <hi>Quae non eſt futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turorum
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17163:65"/> nec praeſentium, ſed praeteritorum tantùm: ſenſus praeſentium, ſpes futurorum;</hi> which is not of things to come, nor of things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but only of things paſt, ſenſe onely having to doe with things preſent; Hope alone being in expectation of things to come.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:17163:65"/>
            <head>Of the Vnderſtanding, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall part, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Branch of Prudence. <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I will not be ſo ſcrupulous, as to make a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus</hi> and <hi>Intelligentia,</hi> the one being taken by ſome for the Vnderſtanding facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the other for the Act of the Vnderſtanding; but both two-fold, Divine, and Humane. The Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect is a property of God, whereby hee knowes all things moſt perfectly in himſelfe. Which Divine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17163:66"/> Intellect of his, may bee underſtood foure manner of wayes. Firſt, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of God is a moſt ſimple act, therefore God doth not underſtand <hi>diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo à noto ad ignotum;</hi> but by apprehending the matter ſimply, and by it ſelfe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the Vnderſtanding of God, underſtandeth God himſelf directly, and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: but other things, <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm in exemplari,</hi> as they are certaine Images of God. Thirdly, all diſtinctions of times God doth underſtand at one act, <hi>Simùl &amp; Semèl,</hi> thoſe things, which wee call things paſt, preſent, and to come. Laſtly, the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandes all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, nothing contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17163:66"/> or by Opinion.</p>
            <p>Many have beene of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that <hi>Intellectus,</hi> and <hi>Opinio</hi> are all one. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute this, <hi>Saint Bernard</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">D. Bern.</note> that <hi>Multi ſuam opinionem, intellectum putaverunt, &amp; erraverunt: &amp; quaedam opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio poteſt putari intellectus, intellectus opinio non poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unde hoc accidit profectò, quia haec falli, &amp; fallere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ille non poteſt: aut ſi falli potuit, intellectus non fuit, ſed opinio. Verus nempè intellectus certam habet non modò veritatem, ſed notiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am veritatis;</hi> Many have thought their opinion to be Vnderſtanding, and have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; And ſome opinion may bee thought to bee Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; but underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot bee taken for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17163:67"/> which commeth to paſſe certainely, becauſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion may deceive, and be deceived: Vnderſtanding cannot: or, if it could bee deceived, it were not Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, but Opinion. For true Vnderſtanding hath not onely a certaine truth: but a knowledge of the truth: But Divine Intellect is no part of my Prudence; mine is Humane, which is defined by <hi>Saint Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Bern.</note> to be <hi>Rei cujuſcunque inviſibilis, certa, &amp; manifeſta notitia.</hi> An inviſible, certaine, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt knowledge of any thing. Others thinke that the underſtanding is a power of the Rationall ſoule, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man doth perceive, judge and know Intelligibles, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially Vniverſalls: and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17163:67"/> here is unfolded the Triple office of the Vnderſtanding, <hi>Percipere, Iudicare, &amp; Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere.</hi> Thus (according to <hi>Saint Auguſtine) Intellectus eſt vis animae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>quae ſub viſu non cadentia percipit: quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodùm ipſa quoque anima, ſenſus adminiculo, corporatas formas intuetur;</hi> The Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is a facultie of the ſoule, which doth perceive things beyond the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſight, or ſenſe: as the ſoule it ſelfe doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold corporeall formes by the aſſiſtance of the ſenſes. Here Philoſophicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſights raiſe a difference <hi>Inter animum, &amp; animam.</hi> Nor is the diſtinction to bee ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for <hi>Animus eſt, quo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus, anima, quâ vivimus;</hi> the mind is it whereby wee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17163:68"/> conſider, and grow wiſe, the ſoule whereby we live, and grow men. Divers trouble themſelves with diviſions of the Intellect; In mine owne opinion,<note place="margin">Pet Mar.</note> 
               <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> gives it the plaineſt, and the beſt: <hi>Vnus vocatur practicus, &amp; alter ſpeculativus, non quaſi ſint duae vires aut fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultates animae, ſed, quia circa objecta ſua ſpeculativa vel practica verſatur intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus, aut ſpeculativus, aut practicus;</hi> The one is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (ſaith hee) the Practicke, the other the Speculative, not, as if they were two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct faculties of the minde, but, becauſe about thoſe things that are Speculative, or Practicke, the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is buſied or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant.<note place="margin">Mag.</note> 
               <hi>Magirus</hi> jumpes
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17163:68"/> with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but doth adde fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is firſt ſeparated <hi>in ſpecie</hi> from the other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoule, next it is ſeparated from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for wee can underſtand without the body, and the Vnderſtanding uſeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Organe of the body, but is freed <hi>Ab omni conſortio ejus.</hi> Laſtly, the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is ſeparable from the ſame, not onely accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to operation, but alſo according to ſubſiſtence: becauſe, the body being taken away, the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſubſiſts, and remaines permanent by it ſelfe. It being therefore plaine, that the Vnderſtanding is a facultie of the ſoule, that it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17163:69"/> hath no certaine Organ in the body, and can ſubſiſt without the body, it muſt be, as the ſoule is. That there is a Vegetative, a Senſitive, and a Rationall Soule, I think few ſo irrationall, but know it. The Vegetative Soule, Trees, and Plants partake of; The Vegetative, and Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Beaſts, Birds, and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes; The Vegetative, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, and a Rationall Soule is in Man alone. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which Rationall Soule, there is a four-fold opinion: The firſt is, That it is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and brought forth, as a part of the Subſtance of God, who inſpireth it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Body, according to that of <hi>Moſes; Inſpiravit in faciem ejus ſpiraculum vitae.</hi> The ſecond is, That it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17163:69"/> from the ſoules of our Parents, and is transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, even as, and when the ſeede is. The third, That the ſoules of men have been from the beginning all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and reſerved in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, afterwards to be ſent into the lower parts, as need ſhould require, and that the bodies of men are formed, and diſpoſed to receive them. The laſt opinion is, That all ſoules are created of God, and infuſed into Men, and that the Creation and Infuſion is effected <hi>Vno eodemque tempore.</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Opinions, mine is, That it is a Myſterie beyond the Philoſophers reach, and not to be underſtood <hi>Abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Numine,</hi> I need not have
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17163:70"/> troubled my ſelfe with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of the Rationall Soule, ſince I am to write onely,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> where it is placed. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith. That it is <hi>Tota in toto, &amp; tota in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet parte;</hi> Which is true concerning the ſoules ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geticall information, but not concerning her Royal Palace of chiefe habitation. <hi>Charown</hi> is of opinion,<note place="margin">Char.</note> That the ſoules Chiefe or Tribunall Seate is in the head, and not in the heart, forgetting, it ſeemes That <hi>Cor eſt primum vivens, &amp; ultimum Moriens:</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her chiefeſt place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, I finde a threefold, and different opinion. The Phyſitions hold her Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſeate in the braine: the Philoſophers in the heart: &amp; ſome Divines (that believe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17163:70"/> the ſoule to be <hi>Ex traduce</hi>) in the blood.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of this variety in opinion concerning the proper ſeate of the ſoule, <hi>Rawlins,</hi> an ingenious Fryer,<note place="margin">Raw.</note> takes occaſion to wonder at the learned, and (as it were) laboured Malice of the Iewes, in purſuing the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule of Chriſt, even till it left his body; For (ſaith he) there being three chiefe opinions, where the ſoule is chiefely ſeated: to wit,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either in the Blood, according to that in Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, <hi>Anima omnis Carnis in ſanguine eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or in the Braine, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noted Phyſitions think.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or in the Heart, as your beſt and ſoundeſt Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers hold.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:17163:71"/>
            <p>That maliciouſly-wicked rabble of Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſees (as if they had beene ſtudied and expert in the ſeverall ſubtilties, and varieties of thoſe ſeverall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions) ſought to force the ſoule of Chriſt out of his body, through thoſe the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt and livelieſt parts of his body; ſeeking, if they could, to let it out</p>
            <p>Firſt, Through his Head, and Braine, by a twiſted Crowne of ſharpe-pointed Thornes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Through his Bloud by Whips &amp; Nayles, in piercing, and tearing the veynes of his body, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his hands and feet.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Through his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heart, when that bloudy Souldier, <hi>Longinus</hi> ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:17163:71"/> if <hi>Rome</hi> miſtake not, ran him through the ſide with his deadly Launce.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſeverall opinions do all carry Truth with them in their ſeverall kindes. For the ſoule hath its ſeat both in the bloud, and in the braine; but Principally, and moſt Radically in the heart. Plain it is, That the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is ſeated with the Soule, and the Soule ſeated in the Heart, and both of them, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, joyned together. Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> obſerves,<note place="margin">D. Baſil.</note> That the Court hath got the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of the Queene, that dwells in it, the Queene the name of the Court; the Heart the attributes of the Soule, the Soule the name of the Heart; ſo that the Soule is where the Heart is,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17163:72"/> the Vnderſtanding inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with them both; Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the words of God to <hi>Solomon,</hi> For I have given thee an Vnderſtanding Heart.<note place="margin">Sir Tho. Ell.</note> 
               <hi>Sir Thomas Elliot,</hi> in his diſputation <hi>Platonicke,</hi> ſaith, That the Heart of Man is the Soules booke, wherein all Thoughts are written. And wee know there are two Veines in the Tongue, the one (as it is thought) hath recourſe to the Heart, the other to the Head: that of the Heart, what it ſuggeſts, it brings up to the Head, where both meete, and deliver over their joynt, and ſeverall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands to the Tongue; Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, <hi>Ex abundantia Cordis os loquitur.</hi> And now will I
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17163:72"/> cloſe up this Point with the words of the ever to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for Learning, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Saint Alban,</hi> who,<note place="margin">Vic. St. Alb.</note> in his Booke entituled The Advancement of Learning, thus ſaith; The Arts Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall are foure in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, divided according to the ends, whereunto they are referred; For Mans la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is to invent that, which is ſought, and propounded; or to judge that, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; or to retaine that, which is judged; or to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver over that, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſo that the Arts muſt bee foure; Art of Enquirie, or Invention; Art of Examination, or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Art of Cuſtody, or Memory; And Art of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, or Tradition. Thus
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17163:73"/> curſorily have I run over the Vnderſtanding. In the next place I am to Write <hi>De Providentia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Of Providence, the third part of Prudence. <hi>CAP. VIII.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concerning Providence. The firſt is the Epicureans, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Vngodly; Who deny, That there is a God, not plainly in Words, but in Heart; and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, deny the Providence of God. The ſecond, is of the Stoicks, Who rightly allow, That all things are
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17163:73"/> by the Providence of God; becauſe nothing is done without the Divine care and knowledge: yet, will they have all things fall out by a fatall neceſſity. The third Opinion is of the Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (which carrieth more truth then the former) who rightly Judge, That all things are done by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God; and yet that ſome things fall out ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually and fatally both; and thoſe were the Ariſtoteli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Platoniſts, and many Schoolemen at this day. And now give me leave to branch forth a diviſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I give you the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. There is a Divine, and an Humane Providence.<note place="margin">Pet. Mar.</note> Divine Providence is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> to be
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17163:74"/> 
               <hi>Ratio quâ deus utitur in rebus dirigendis ad ſuos fines, in quâ definitione non modo notitia, ſed voluntas, &amp; vis id faciendi comprehenſa eſt;</hi> It is (ſaith hee) a reaſon which God uſeth in directing things to his owne ends; in which definition not onely the knowledge, but the will, &amp; power of his doing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. <hi>Providentia dei eſt ipſa divina ratio, in ſummo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Principe (Deo) conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta, quâ is cuncta praeterita &amp; futura videt, &amp; praecognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit: Hoc eſt, Providentia Dei eſt Scientia Dei certa, in ejus mente concepta ab aeterno, de ijs, quae olim facta, &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm futura ſunt neceſſariò &amp; contingentèr;</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God is the very divine reaſon conſtituted in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17163:74"/> God the chiefe Prince of all things, wherby hee ſees and fore-knowes all things paſt, and to come; That is, The Providence of God is the certaine knowledge of God, conceived in his Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding from eternity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe things which were neceſſarily and contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently done in times paſt, or which any time are to come. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> hath it thus; <hi>Eſt facultas Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mar</note> 
               <hi>quâ res omnes dirigit, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducit ad ſuos fines;</hi> Tis a faculty of God, whereby hee directs, and reduces all things to his owne ends. <hi>Trelcatius</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Trel.</note> That Providence is an outward action of God, whereby hee keepeth all and ſeverall things that are done, to that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17163:75"/> end, which he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined according to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of his will, and that, to the end, he might in all and ſeverall things bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified. The efficient cauſe of this Providence or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is the ſame, which is of creation, ſith one, and the ſelfe ſame beginning is of both, from, and by which all things doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and are conſerved, to wit, God the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the love and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Father, is the firſt beginning cauſe: the Sonne, in that hee is the Wiſedome and Word, is the working cauſe, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, in that he is the virtue and power of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Sonne, is the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:17163:75"/> cauſe, <hi>Sicut Adam a nullo homine, Evah ex ſolo homine, &amp; Seth ex utroque; ita Deus pater a nullo, filius ex ſolo patre, &amp; Spiritus Sanctus ex utroque;</hi> Even as <hi>Adam</hi> was from none, <hi>Eve</hi> from man alone, and <hi>Seth</hi> from them both; ſo God the Father is from none, the Sonne from the Father alone, and the Holy Ghoſt from them both. Now the workes of God ſummarily are two; That of the Creation, &amp; that of the Redemption; both theſe workes, as, in the totall, they may appertaine to the Vnity of the Godhead, ſo, in their parts, they may be referred to the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. That of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the Maſſe of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <gap reason="missing" extent="18 pages">
                  <desc>〈18 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:17163:76"/>
            <p> hee may bee in all his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings <hi>Magnanimus actu,</hi> That Britiſh tongues may triumphantly ſay, <hi>Charolus ille Magnus:</hi> &amp; as in my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignes cauſe, I have plaid the Prieſt, So let the Britiſh World bee my Clearkes, and ſay, Amen. That I may alſo pray for them. Otherwiſe, I ſhall but curſe that ſoule, that will not ſay ſo. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am loth to divulge the utmoſt of my thoughts; yet I feare, that tongue will burne in unquenchable fire, that dare preſume to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize his Soveraigns name, or detract from his worth. And this dare I juſtifie. For he cannot be a true ſervant to God, that beares not a true heart to his King; But,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17163:76"/> mee thinkes I heare <hi>Bleſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Ble.</note> 
               <hi>Pro regibus orare eſt nova traditio,</hi> To pray for Kings is a new tradition; I wonder hee, or any dare broach ſuch new Hereſie, ſince wee are commanded by <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and <hi>S. Paul,</hi> to pray for them which are in Authority, eſpecially for our Supreame Soveraigne. <hi>Pro Rege quaſi praecellenti.</hi> When <hi>Abiſhai</hi> would have ſlaine <hi>Saul,</hi> the mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>David, David</hi> ſayd to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> Deſtroy him not, for who can ſtretch foorth his hand againſt the Lords Annointed, and be guiltleſſe, It was King <hi>Iohns</hi> very caſe in the viewing the Caſtle of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> as is to bee ſeene in our Hiſtory. And thus much for the Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:17163:77"/> Duties betwixt Kings and their Subjects.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>The mutuall Duties betweene Parents and their Children. <hi>CAP. X.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Children, ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> are not for the Parents, but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for the children; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin we therefore with their Office and Duty, ſince theirs is the Precedency. When the Childe is borne, let not the Mother (though good in diſpoſition) nurſe any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhe nurſe all. I am not againſt the generall Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if it were not meete
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17163:77"/> for a Mother to nurſe her owne Childe: Yet this I conceive, that if ſhe ſhould nurſe one, and refuſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe ſhould with much partiality incline to one, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then another. For Womens affections are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times tranſported be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Judgement, And let the Fathers intentions bee never ſo upright, yet the Mothers ſurvivorſhip may finde out new inventions to performe her Naturall Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Chooſe, if you be droven to a choice for your Nurſe, a Woman Witty, Handſome, and if you can (having the two former qualities) Honeſt; For that Childe, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth nutriment from his Foſter Mother, will goe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:17163:78"/> neere to Sympathize with her in condition. And now the Horne-booke appeares. If thou haſt Daughters, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, Dancing, Needle-working may ſerve turne to keepe them from Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; They are hardly got, and quickly loſt. To make them ſchollers, were frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, it being by ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That Learning in a Woman, is like a Sunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall in a Grave. And we have a Caveat given us from our late <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs;<note place="margin">King Iames</note> It hath like opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make Women lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as to make <hi>Foxes</hi> tame, which only teacheth them to ſteale more cunningly. The poſſibility is not equall, for where it doth one good, it doth twenty harme. True
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17163:78"/> it is, divers Women have beene very well learned. I have read, that <hi>Zenobia</hi> Queene of the <hi>Palmerians,</hi> being skilfull in the Greeke, Latine, &amp; <hi>Aegyptian</hi> tongues, taught them to her two ſons, and wrote an Epitome of the Eaſterne parts. <hi>Cornelia</hi> taught her two ſonnes the Gracchi, the Latine tongue. And <hi>Aretia</hi> taught her ſon <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> philoſophy, but he proved a Sycophantical Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. Indeed knowledge in a Woman commonly purchaſeth more Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience then profit. <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli gratia.</hi> A Romane and a Grecian Embaſſadour, meeting in the Senate of the Rhodians; the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian ſpake theſe words; True it is, Romane, you
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17163:79"/> are bold in Armes, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull in Sciences, for the Women of <hi>Greece</hi> are more skilfull in Learning, then the Men of <hi>Rome</hi> in Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons. Theſe words cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Warre in <hi>Sicily.</hi> At laſt the Rhodians perſwaded, that thoſe Warres ſhould be ended, not by Weapons, but by Feminine Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It was like to be a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Piece, when Women tooke it in hand, Stout War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers they are, to end Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours Quarrels. The Arguments my Author no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not; Nor do I know his Reaſon, But certainely, as farre as they tended to a Logicall Diſputation, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and over excellent. Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſes, are the fitteſt Bookes for Womens Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:17163:79"/> For there they may rectifie their Deformities, and take Counſell, which may be the beſt way to ſhew that part, which is beſt. Yet I would have no Woman ſo farre dote on thoſe Bookes, as to offer up her Morning Sacrifice to them, Eying her ſelfe ſo long, till <hi>Narciſſus</hi> like, ſhe fall in love with her owne Shadow, I do hate this Face Phyſicke.<note place="margin">Diog.</note> 
               <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaid to one, that had perfumed his Locks, Be carefull your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous Head procure you not a ſtinking Life. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, with <hi>Abſolon,</hi> you take no Pride in your Locks, leſt you be inſnared by them; For I believe theſe Daubed ones are in eaſie poſſibility, to be Polluted
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17163:80"/> ones.<note place="margin">Laert.</note> I like <hi>Laertius</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>Optimi ſunt odores, qui odorant Mores, alitèr non ſunt flores, ſed faetores;</hi> Strong perfumes argue guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of ſome loathſome Savour; Glorious outſides, imply ſome inward Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that would faine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape notice: overmuch Ornament: importing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; If ſhee be Faire, ſhe muſt be Proud, and ſhe cannot be Proud unleſſe ſhe love her Face, which is the better beloved, when repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in a flattering Glaſſe. In a word, the Learnedſt Woman, that ever was, her knowledge being Weighed with an indifferent Mans, will prove like the Woman and the Feather in the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Scales,
<q>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:17163:80"/>
                  <l>Where if the Cardinall played right,</l>
                  <l>The Woman was three Grains too light.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, for all this, I muſt confeſſe, I would not have them altogether Illiterate. Let them Read, and Write, but not Indite: Casket them not up for Holy Reliques; but when nature hath made them fit for the Rites of Marriage, marry them, leſt they ſave you a labour. And there is an end with them, and their Education.</p>
            <p>If thou haſt Sons, in the firſt place, be carefull of their Paedagogue, That hee be Modeſt, Sober, Learned; And be ſure that hee have a good Forme of Teaching, leſt the ſucceeding Maſters
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:17163:81"/> ſhould have more to doe, to Vnteach, then to Teach. <hi>Dimo</hi> the Muſitian deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alwaies a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of them whom others taught, then of them, who never learned any thing. In this Proviſion of Tutors, the Gentrie are farre ſhort of their Inferiors, as it will appeare by the words of <hi>Quintilian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quin.</note> urged by Sir <hi>Thomas Elliot.</hi> And theſe are they, Common Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth, That no Man will put his Sonne to a Butcher, to learne; or bind him Prentice to a Traveller, if hee intend to make him a Scholler: or if hee will have him a cunning Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, will firſt binde him Prentice to a Tinker; Theſe things Poore Men are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:17163:81"/> in, and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Gentlemen (who would have their Sonnes by excellent learning come to Honour) or for ſparing of Coſt, or for lacke of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearch for a good Schoolemaſter, wilfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Children; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to be taught that Learning, which would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſixe or ſeaven Yeares to be forgotten; By which time the moſt part of that Age is ſpent, wherein the chiefeſt ſharpeneſſe of Wit, and alſo then approacheth the ſtubborne Age, when the Childe brought up in Pleaſure, diſdaineth Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. And herein Poore men and Great men differ, the one eſteeming Learning an Honour, the other (too
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17163:82"/> often) rather a Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then an Ornament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diod.</note>
               <hi>Diodorus</hi> the Sicilian Writeth, That the Law-maker <hi>Charondas</hi> appointed, that all the Children of the City ſhould learne their Letters at the charges of the Common-wealth, which was to maintaine Publick Maſters, to teach both Poor and Rich. Like to this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome are our Free-ſchooles in <hi>England,</hi> where, though perhaps the Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or Schoole-maſters may very well inſtruct a multitude in learning, Yet he or they can hardly order them in good marners. For what are two men, or three, at the moſt, to a giddy-headed company of Boyes? My opinion is (if conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency)
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17163:82"/> will permit) Let them learne firſt at home, in thoſe <hi>annis pubeſcentibus.</hi> Then your owne eyes may ſee their education. <hi>Licurgus</hi> his whelps, both of a Litter, may give ſufficient ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, The one being well educated, would kill a Hare; The other inſtead of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, would fall to gnawing of bones which he found in the High-way. When <hi>Antipater</hi> demanded of the <hi>Spartans</hi> fifty Children for Hoſtages, they replyed, That they had rather let him have a double portion of thoſe which were at their full yeares; For they knew the ingenuity of their Men, but not (by reaſon of good education) what their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren might come to Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17163:83"/> is <hi>Prima, Secunda, Tertia pars vitae.</hi> That croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe which a Tree hath in it's tender growth, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth dayly with the growth of the Tree, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them well in their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they will Savour of it in their Age, According to the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quo Semèl eſt imbuta recens</l>
               <l>Servabit odorem</l>
               <l>Teſta diù.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>And now, I ſuppoſe, my Striplings are formally clad, and togated, newly arrived at the Vniverſitie, where before they are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, the Colleges and Halls, they muſt bee ſent for home, to be cocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in their Fathers par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; if they ſuffer them to ſtay ſo long, as to ſee the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:17163:83"/> Library, they ſuppoſe they are able to diſcourſe of the Vniverſities great Learning, in that very houre they eyed the Bookes, though not profited their Vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. But every man may take notice; That perfect ſchollers are perfect Men, halfe ſchollers halfe Men, no Schollers no Men. For the illiterate are like Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, or like a picture, which cauſeth this Motto, This is the Effigies of ſuch a man. What a lamentable ſight is it, to ſee a good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Body want an Head-piece? <hi>O quale Caput, ſed non habet Cerebrum.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without Learning hath loſt it's eye-ſight; And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is leſſe paine to learne in youth, then to be
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:17163:84"/> ignorant in old age; <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta hominis ſine literis mors eſt, &amp; vivi hominis is ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura:</hi> The life of a man without knowledge is a death, and the ſepulchre of a living man (ſaith <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic.</note>) Wit without Learning is like a Tree without fruite; As an untilled field, ſo is the minde without Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, finding the defect of Learning in himſelfe, utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe words to his ſon, That an unlearned Prince was a Crowned Aſſe. If it be ſo with Kings, what is it with Inferiours? Now there are ſome Pretenders to Learning, who by their ſilken Out-ſides would have the World ſuppoſe they had Golden Inſides,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17163:84"/> whoſe Cringed knees, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke geſtures, with a whole rabble of Superlative foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries (prating as amply, as unneceſſarily, their Tongues being Gentlemen-Vſhers to their Wits, ſtill going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) leade vulgar Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into Labyrinths of amazements, Who onely meaſure Inward Sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies by Outward Formes, or Fortunes, Eſteeming them moſt Wiſe, who are moſt Fantaſtically deckt, Rich, Honourable; As if theſe things without an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Magnified their Wits, and with an Eſtate did put the World in minde of their Fortunes. But what hath my Pen to doe with Folly? Yet why ſhould I ſay ſo? Since the common Opinion
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:17163:85"/> is (urge what I can to the contrary) No Wiſedome without Wealth.</p>
            <p>Yet I like not to ſee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting Ignorance domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere over poore Schollers, Who are forced to come ſneaking in with Paradoxes of Poverty. But if you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is ſayd by <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides</hi> in his Eccleſiaſticus, You ſhall find the words and actions of the Rich farre ſurpaſſing thoſe of the poore; So that, make mee Rich, I muſt bee Juſt, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, Honourable, Wiſe, <hi>Et quid non.</hi> For Virtue in poverty is like a goodly Ship ready rig'd, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſaile for want of Wind. But <hi>Quo vado.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To tell you of all the Kings, and Emperours, that
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:17163:85"/> were Schollers, and Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Learning, were but to fill up my Papers with Proper Names. I reſerve them for ſome other, though not for my better uſes. I will onely urge the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Claudius Caeſar, Coſroes</hi> King of the Perſians, the Veſpaſians, <hi>Ptolomy</hi> King of the Aegyptians, and the good Emperour <hi>Trajane,</hi> who at his owne charges maintained five Hundred Children at Schoole, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to baniſh Ignorance. It is obſerved, That, from the death of <hi>Domitianus</hi> the Emperour, untill the raigne of <hi>Commodus</hi> (comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the raigne of ſixe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) all were Learned, or ſingular Favourers, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancers of Learning. It was
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:17163:86"/> a wiſe anſwer of <hi>Alexander,</hi> when queſtion was made, what ſhould be put into the rich Cabinet of <hi>Darius,</hi> hee anſwered, <hi>Homers</hi> Workes. And reaſon good; For <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> hath given more men their Living, then <hi>Sylla, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus.</hi> Happy then is it, when Kings are Philoſophers, or Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Kings. It was <hi>Varroes</hi> good fortune to light upon <hi>Anthony,</hi> who, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to die, for his Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was pardoned by him, uttering theſe words, <hi>Vivat Varro vir doctiſs mus;</hi> And <hi>Alexander</hi> was never more renowned in all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, then he was in that of <hi>Thebes,</hi> when he ſold all the Free-men (Prieſts onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) and in the greatneſſe
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:17163:86"/> of that Maſſacre, not onely gave charge for the ſaving of <hi>Pindarus</hi> the Poet; but alſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w himſelfe, both him, his houſe, and family undamni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Whoſoever hath but ſeene Hiſtory, ſhall not onely find the Learning of theſe, and many more, but their well wiſhing, and bounty towards it. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive therefore, that Parents are bound to lend their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hands, that their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may be inſtructed, <hi>Tàm Moribus, quàm Doctrinâ: tàm Doctrinâ quàm Moribus;</hi> Otherwiſe the Childrens faults will light upon the Parents heads. And by the Law <hi>Falcidia,</hi> if the Child commit an offence, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould be puniſhed. To this purpoſe was that of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17163:87"/> 
               <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who being to buy commodities of the Father, and the Sonne, the Sonne ſwore, that <hi>Diogenes</hi> offered leſſe, then it coſt his Father. <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſtrucke the Father for the Sonnes oath, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demanded wherefore hee ſtrucke him; <hi>Diogenes</hi> replyed becauſe he had not inſtructed his Sonne better, then to commit ſuch an offence. But in point of Schollerſhip I might here urge <hi>Architrenius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Archi.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>At dijs paulò minor plebes Phaebeia ſecund'os</l>
                  <l>Vix metit eventus, quicquid ſerit undi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tortu</l>
                  <l>Vapulat adverſis. —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Labourer bliſters but his Hands, but the Scholler
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17163:87"/> his Braines; And when all is done, he is but as a Fiſh caſt upon the ſands, that muſt ſtay, till the Tide of others Good-will flowes. Indeed there are too many Politicks, that hold it a needleſſe thing to be any way indulgent to Schollers, (Poverty being thought to be their Naturall Patrimony) terming them by the title of <hi>Scholaſtici.</hi> And ſome others thinke ſchollerſhip to bee but the Emblem of beggary (though I hold it but a beggarly opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) ſo that Schollers me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, like Ciphers, ſtand for nothing. It is reported, that one of the Philoſophers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered a ſtock of money to a friend of his upon this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That if it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his Children ſhould bee
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:17163:88"/> Fooles, he ſhould deliver it unto them; but if Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, then to the Common-people. A ſtrange reſolution from ſo wiſe a Man, which perhaps drove an other of the Philoſophers into a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the World ſo induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly heaping up Treaſure, and being ſo negligent, whom to leave it to. And here abruptly I breake off, leſt the proſecution of my Diſcourſe ſhould beget of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, where I meant none; For by a due proceeding, I ſhould fall upon ſome points which are Orthodoxall, if the Fathers of the Church, and Moderne Writers of the beſt ſort, as alſo Expoſitors as well of Antiquity, as of latter times, of ſeverall reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and of all ſorts neere
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:17163:88"/> an hundred bee of validity to have ſteered my ſeverall ſilenced Tenets.</p>
            <p>I chooſe rather to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that grand Politicians adviſe, who bids me not to come, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:17163:89"/>
            <p>A And thus I paſſe from the deſcendent to the aſcendent dutie.</p>
            <p>And here, in reſpect of mine owne obedience, as well as others, I will bee more freely bold to ſet downe truth, knowing that none but Children and Fooles can take exception. Where then lies this dutie aſcendent? Vndoubtedly in the Childs awfull ſervice and obſervance, both of his Parents perſons, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts: For thereto are Children bound, both by naturall inſtinct, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall injunction. Nature teacheth their reſpect and obedience towards thoſe, who gave them being: And the God of nature enjoynes them no leſſe in the firſt
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:17163:89"/> Commandement of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table. And the elder of the two Sonnes in the Goſpell ſhewes by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his dutious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour there, what is due from the Sonne to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is ſervice, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens. If therefore Parents performe their duties, a curſe will light the heavier on the Children, that doe not really act theirs; And let them bee ſure to receive it corporally in this, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually in the World to come.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Plutarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut.</note> that great Moraliſt ſaith; That the Child is not bound to his Parents, of whom hee hath not received ſome good thing. In which point, I
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:17163:90"/> doubt whether it holds truth on the Childs part, for he is bound abſolutely to obey: But certainely 'tis true on the Parents, they ought to doe good to their Children, and not to grieve, or provoke them, (if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> be to bee believed) but howſoever to doe them all manner of good, unleſſe they will bee worſe then the worſt of the Iewes; For even of them hath our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaid, Yee your ſelves being evill know how to give good gifts to your Children. But I proceed in Childrens duties,<note place="margin">Baſt.</note> and muſt tell them, that <hi>Baſtingius</hi> reduces the duties of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren towards their Parents unto three principall Heads: The firſt is, <hi>De Obedientiâ,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:17163:90"/> quam liberi debent ipſorum fidelibus, &amp; pijs praeceptis;</hi> The Second <hi>de Fide, nempe, ne illos pauperes negligant, ſed ut viciſsim ijs praemia nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis retribuant;</hi> The Third, <hi>de Amore, hoc eſt, Vt eorum vitia &amp; mores tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, &amp; piâ quâdam indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiâ ad ſenectutis ſordes, &amp; errata conniveant;</hi> I leave this for the Reader to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate, and come to the words of <hi>Herolt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her.</note> who determines their duties in ſixe things, <hi>Filij in ſex tenentur parenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis, ſive ſint vivi, ſive mortui. Primò, Tenentur ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vire eis corporalitèr, ſcilicet, cum proprio ſuo corpore: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo, Tenentur filij parentes eorum diligere ex corde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra hoc faciunt, qui parentes odorunt, &amp; optant ijs mortem,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17163:91"/> ut eorum haereditatem parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipent; Quod eſt valdè re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibile, &amp; grave pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Tertiò, Tenentur paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus dulcitèr, &amp; reverentèr reſpondere, cum ab ipſis corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piuntur. Quartò, Filij tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur parentibus in temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; corporalibus ſubveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Quintò, Filij tenentur pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus, in his, quae ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; ſalutem ipſorum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. Sextò, Tenentur filij parentibus defunctis ſubve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire, &amp; animas parentum ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cum Miſsis, Eleëmoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; Orationibus de Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio liberare;</hi> Sonnes in ſixe things are bound to their Parents, whether they be alive or dead; Firſt, they are bound to ſerve them Corporally, to wit, with their owne Body. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:17163:91"/> Children are bound to love their Parents, with their Heart: Againſt this they tranſgreſſe which hate their Parents, and wiſh their death, that they may parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate of their inheritance; Which is excedingly to bee reprehended, and a Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sinne; (and in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſuch a Sinne as will hardly be forgiven.) Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are bound mildly, and reverently to render an anſwer, when they are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected of them. Fourthly, they are bound to relieve their Parents in Temporall, and Corporall things. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Children are bound to obey their Parents in thoſe things, which belong unto their good and ſafety. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Children are bound to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17163:92"/> helpe their dead Parents, to free their Soules out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory by ſaying Maſſe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Almes, and making Prayers; The Fourth I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve if need requires. The laſt ſhall never bee any part of my Creed. Howſoever let all Children remember the firſt Commandement of the Second Table, dividing it ſelfe into two particulars; into a Precept, and a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or rather a Reward, which is annexed unto this Commandement, and none elſe. The Precept (Honour thy Father and thy Mother) the Reaſon or the Reward [That thy dayes may bee long in the Land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee:] Now, the word for Honour in the Originall ſignifies
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:17163:92"/> 
               <hi>Aggravare;</hi> So that wee muſt <hi>Addere Pretium</hi> and <hi>Addere Pondus,</hi> and ſo <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem:</hi> make it a matter of weight to honour them. And ſeeing they beare the perſons of God, they muſt not be ſet ſlightly by.<note place="margin">Phil.</note> And here by the way <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew conceiveth this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to bee halfe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, halfe Humane; and ſo would have that, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes God, to be in the firſt Table, that which belongs to our Neighbour in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table. Parents queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe ought to be reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and obeyed; As it is in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> the <hi>Kings, Luke,</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Taurus</hi> the Philoſopher, when the Father and the Sonne came to him about a
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:17163:93"/> Controverſie, the Sonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Magiſtrate, the Father none, appointed, that the Father ſhould ſit on that one ſtoole hee had, till the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion were decided, whether of them ought to have the place. Sufficient might bee urged for the manifeſtation of this point, but all to this purpoſe. Offend not thy Parents in Thought, Word, or Deed; In thy Thoughts harbour not the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit againſt them; In thy Deeds doe not any thing to grieve them; In thy Words ſpeake not amiſſe of them. Remember what <hi>Chryſolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Lingua in capite eſt caput mali;</hi> The Tongue in the Head is the Head of evill; eſpecially in this caſe. And this Dutie ſtands as
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:17163:93"/> well in the Action, as in the Manner of the Action; And neither to be omitted, and in both be ſure thou art not arraigned at the Barre, and proved guilty: for my part, I had better; nay, rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe <hi>Iſaakes</hi> Burden, then offend my Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> Thus have I ſhewed the reſpective duties, both from Parents to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and from Children to their Parents. And thus I ſhake hands on both ſides, wiſhing both Parents and Children anſwerable unto what I have wrote; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren eſpecially: For by the Moſaicall Law, You ſhall feare every Man his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his Father. And in the <hi>Proverbes</hi> you may find, Honour thy Father,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:17163:94"/> that begate thee, and thy Mother that bare thee: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely then, the Child is in a litle deeper bond of dutie, then the Parents, if the Wiſedome of <hi>Solomon</hi> failed him not, when hee thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, Honour thy Father with thy whole Heart, and forget not the ſorrowes of thy Mother. Remember that thou waſt begot of them, and how canſt thou recompenſe them the things that they have done for thee? And thus much for this part of Providence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:17163:94"/>
            <head>Of the mutuall Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Maſters and their Servants. <hi>CAP. XI.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd now a word or two betweene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Families, and their Servants. And Firſt for the Maſter. The Maſter of a Family, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> exerciſeth a three-fold Power; A Power Regall over his Children; A Power Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſteriall over his Servants; And a Power Ariſtocrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call over his Wife; which is not after his owne Will, but agreeable to the Honour and Dignity of the Married eſtate. But this is not the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:17163:95"/> Duty, which is urged in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> If any provide not for his owne, eſpecially thoſe of his owne Houſhold, hee hath denyed his Faith, and is worſe then an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell. A ſingle proviſion of Victualls is not ſufficient to ſupply this want; There is a care to be had of their Soules; (For the greateſt part of them have little of their owne) I meane not Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanically to Catechize them; For that is <hi>Officium Sacerdotis;</hi> But, as neere as you can, to beate downe Sinne in them, Eſpecially, that of Swearing. Suffer them not to enterlard their Diſcourſe with Oathes: For believe it, the hand of God will light heavie upon
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:17163:95"/> that Houſe, where Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers dwell. O Barre not then thy Servant of his due. If hee can ſay unto thee, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did unto <hi>Laban,</hi> Theſe twenty yeares have I beene with thee; thy Ewes and thy Shee-goats have not caſt their Yong, and the Rams of thy flocke have I not eaten; That which was torne of Beaſts, I brought not unto thee, I bare the loſſe of it. Of my hand didſt thou require it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtollen by day, or ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by night. Thus I was, in the day the Drought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed mee, and the Froſt by night, and my ſleepe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from mine Eyes. Thus have I beene twenty yeares in the Houſe, I ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thee fourteene yeares
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:17163:96"/> for thy two Daughters, and ſixe yeares for thy Cattell; and thou haſt changed my wages ten times. If hee can ſay thus, give him not then a bleare-eyed <hi>Leah,</hi> for a beautifull <hi>Rachel:</hi> In a word, barre him not of ought, that is his due.</p>
            <p>Now, for the Servants Duty towards his Maſter, it is foure-fold. Firſt, In executing well his Maſters Commandes, and Acting them diligently. Secondly, In not beguiling. Thirdly, In not reporting that before his face, which hee will not juſtifie behinde his backe. Laſtly, In ſeeking all things for his Maſters good, in his Goods, and otherwiſe. This laſt Duty in the chiefeſt Points thereof is two-fold.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:17163:96"/> Firſt, In not harſhly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to his Maſters words, (for nothing is ſo odious as a ſcurrilous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, eſpecially, from an Inferiour.) Secondly, In keeping his Maſters ſecrets at home and abroad: But by the way, Hee ſhall not locke up his Secrets ſafely, that makes choice of his Servants Heart for a Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. I muſt confeſſe hee is like a Ladder, aſcending and deſcending; bound like a Shadow, neither to be lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger nor ſhorter: His Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being rather a badge of Servitude, then Devotion; And when all is done, hee is but like him, who in a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters night takes a long ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber over a dying fire, as loath to depatt from it; yet
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:17163:97"/> parts thence as cold, as when hee firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> downe. As for his Duty, you may reade it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> divers places of Holy Writ, eſpecially<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Geneſis, the Epiſtle to the Epheſians, Coloſſians, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp;c. I might here give them a Morall Inſtruction, but they will performe what they liſt, ſay what you will, they will doe what they pleaſe. And thus much for Providence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:17163:97"/>
            <head>Of Subtilty of Vnderſtanding, by ſome eſteemed a Branch of Prudence, but indeed an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to its Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall part. <hi>CAP. XII.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Come now to write <hi>De Aſtutiâ mentis,</hi> which (as was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſaid) I conceived to be an Appendix of the three former Species of Prudence: Yet will I allow it a diſtinct Definition, <hi>Aſtutia mentis eſt, quâ in rebus induſtrijs cautum captatur conſilium, &amp; acutè diſcernitur, quid bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quid malum, quid uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, quid incommodum;</hi> The Subtilty of the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is that, whereby wee
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:17163:98"/> take wary Counſell in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious matters, and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually diſcerne, what is good, what evill, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, what incommodious. But ſuch is our broken-bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied Age, that this <hi>Aſtutia</hi> is turned into <hi>Verſutia,</hi> and wee terme thoſe moſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtute, which are moſt Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute.<note place="margin">D. Aug.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a difference betweene them. For (ſaith hee) <hi>Aſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eſt quiddam, quod nùnc in bonam, nùnc in malam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem accipitur; Verſutia eſt obſervatio noſtri commodi in aliquâ re cum alterius detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento; Aſtutia</hi> is a ſubtilty, which is taken ſometime in a good Senſe, ſometime in in a bad. <hi>Verſutia</hi> is a crafty heeding our owne profit with anothers dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage;
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:17163:98"/> And this is called Callidity. The end of this baſe craft is, Firſt to get Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, then Honour. The way to attaine unto theſe is, by that ugly, uncouth Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (Diſſimulation or Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) which becauſe it lights caſually on my Pen. A word or two of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:17163:99"/>
            <head>Of divers ends of the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings Subtilty, and meanes thereto, and firſt of the High-way Flattery. <hi>CAP. XIII.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is the old Sicknes of the Roman Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and the moſt Peſtilent contagion of our Britiſh Nation.</p>
            <p>The Originall of this Flattery firſt came from the Devill, the Devill put it over to the Serpent, the Serpent left it to the Woman: Where it had its beginning, it is probable, it will have its ending. And here,<note place="margin">Com.</note> by the way, <hi>Petrus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtor,</hi>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:17163:99"/> in his Scholaſticall Hiſtory, gives us this note; That at the time, when the Serpent tempted the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, hee was ſtraight, and upright like a man, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by the Curſe hee was caſt downe to the Earth to glide along thereon. To this purpoſe (ſaith <hi>Beda</hi>) the Devill choſe a Serpent,<note place="margin">Bed.</note> that had a face like a Woman, becauſe <hi>Similia ſimilibus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaudant,</hi> that like may be pleaſing to like. And Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> obſerves,<note place="margin">Cyr.</note> That Mans firſt deſtruction was in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, when the Rib was taken out of him to make Woman: So that the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning of our firſt Mother, hath cauſed multitudes of her Sonnes to looſe their hearts; For ever ſince that
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:17163:100"/> time Sinne aſſailes the heart there, where it wants that Rib for defence. And the holy Father <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſeemes to bee very angry with our Grand-mother <hi>Eve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Ambr.</note> wiſhing that either <hi>Eves</hi> Tongue had beene out, or both hers, and <hi>Adams</hi> eares ſtopped, before either the Woman had liſtned to the Serpent, or the Man to the beguiled Woman, <hi>Vtinam aut ſurdus Adam fuiſſet, aut Eva obmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſſet, ille ne vocem uxoris audiret; iſta ne loquatur ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito;</hi> Would to God, ſaith he, <hi>Adam</hi> had been deafe, or <hi>Eve</hi> dumbe, hee deafe in not liſtning to his Wives Serpentine Tongue, or ſhee Tongue-tied, that ſhe could not have ſpoken the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Language to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:17163:100"/> 
               <hi>Viciſſemus, ſi Eva ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiſſet;</hi> We had beene hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, ſaith hee, and ſtill kept Paradiſe, could the Woman but have kept her Tongue in her Head, which Tongue hath ſo ſorely broken Mans head, that all the Balſome in the World can never heale ſo deepe a Wound. But to the purpoſe. <hi>Adulatio eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſus delectandi alios verbis, vel factis;</hi> Flattery is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of delighting others by Words, or Deeds; or, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulatio eſt peccatum ex ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone vanae laudis alicui exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitae, intentione complacendi; laudare enim aliquem, qui non eſt laudandus, vel plus quam eſt laudandus, vel non eo fine, quo fieri debet, pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, ſecundum Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alex.</note> Adulation is a Sinne
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:17163:101"/> uſed to any with the ſpeech of vaine praiſe, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of pleaſing; For to praiſe any one, which is not to be praiſed, or more then he is praiſe-worthy, or not to that end, whereto it ought to be done, is a ſinne, if the Author erre not.<note place="margin">D. Greg.</note> Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> ſpeaking of the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Locuſts, ſaith, <hi>Locuſtae vocabulo linguae adulantis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primitur;</hi> By the name of the Locuſt, the Tongue of the Flatterer is expreſt, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorata eſt herba terrae, et quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid pomorum in arboribus fuit;</hi> By the firſt was onely devoured the Graſſe of the Earth, and the fertility of Trees; But theſe Flatterers, <hi>Terrenorum hominum mentes ſi bona aliqua proferre conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant, haec immoderatiùs lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dando
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:17163:101"/> corrumpunt,</hi> Corrupt by immoderate praiſing the Vnderſtanding of Men, if they regard to publiſh ought that is good. The Locuſts laſted in <hi>Aegypt</hi> but three dayes; this is the cuſtomary vice of every day. The Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts were blowne away with a Weſt Wind into the Red Sea: no one Wind, no not all the Winds can blow theſe Diabolicke Servants to their Maſter the Devill, till there be no more Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon Earth.</p>
            <p>But ſome may allege Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for authority of diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, becauſe he would pleaſe the Iewes in <hi>Timothy,</hi> and not circumciſe <hi>Titus</hi> to pleaſe the Gentiles. A Queſtion needing no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; For it was to ſave all,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:17163:102"/> 
               <hi>Non ſimulantis aſtu, ſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patientis affectu;</hi> Not by feigned Diſſimulation, but by compaſſionate Affection. I would willingly here ſhake hands with it, but I am loath to part with it, many doe ſo dearely love it, which makes me tell you, It is the poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Mans Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the Feeder of humors, the whole Volume of it is bound up in the Vellome Cover of Deceit; its acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are worſe then Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Beaſts or Birds, the one doe prey but upon the dead Bodies, the other upon the living Soules. The Reports thereof are like Ecchoes, ſtill imperfect, ſuch ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes that gaine-ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yeelding with your Body, the Looking-glaſſes
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:17163:102"/> that repreſent every thing, that is ſet againſt them: <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melion</hi> like, having all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours but White, all Points but Honeſty. A Flatterer, as ſome ſay, is either an Ape by imitation; For hee will ſooth a Man, till he have got ſomewhat by him: or a Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow by Deceit; For hee quickly paſſeth by: Or a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliske by ſtinging; For with his very ſight hee woundeth a Man: He is that <hi>Mus cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtris,</hi> that ſtill nibles on the hard Rinde of ſowre Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but when he cometh to thoſe, that are ſweet and wholeſome, his Stomacke fals into a loathing. Indeed Flatterers are like Taylors, who will tell you, that your Clothes are fit, when you muſt needs know better
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:17163:103"/> then they. Wee might therefore paint out Flattery, as the Philoſophers did For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, diverſly, as ſhee was to them, but certainly good to none. <hi>Eele</hi>-like, never yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding good hold-faſt. They do, as <hi>Ioab</hi> did to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> embrace to kill. It is the Aſpe, that kills us ſleeping, that <hi>Syrens</hi> voyce, whoſe Raviſhing is Murthering. Thoſe then, that take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be commended by Flatterers, one may take their Vnderſtandings in Purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets. Yet I grieve with Pittie, and pittie them with Griefe, who had rather be ſoothed, then adviſed: ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing more willingly to the Tongue of Flattery, then to the Heart of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, ſo that a <hi>Non-merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:17163:103"/> paraſite</hi> ſhall obtaine a Sun-ſhine admiſſion, when dejected deſert ſhall bee forced to freeze in atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and pine away in fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Expectation.</p>
            <p>But let each Wiſe man ſcorne thoſe, the Clocke of whoſe Tongue is not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Diall of their Hearts. Let him baniſh ſuch Trencher-flies, that waite more for Lucre, then for Love; For my part it ſhall alwayes be in my Litany, From them all the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver mee. But now a dayes I muſe the Myſterie of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is not made a Science, ſince it is ſo Liberally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. The time hath been, when Flatterers have beene altogether ruinated; <hi>Philip,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> baniſhed
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:17163:104"/> them from their Courts. The Athenians put <hi>Tyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> to death, becauſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate with <hi>Darius</hi> hee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted after the Perſian man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> contemned it ſo much, that he would not ſuffer his Servants to kneele, nor <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſuffer his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to call him Lord. King <hi>Canutus</hi> being, as it were, Deified by Flatterers, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one day on the Sands, at a flowing Water, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Waves, that they ſhould not touch his feete, no ſooner had hee ſpoken, but the Sea daſhed him: Ye ſee now my Lords (ſaith hee) what reaſon you have to extoll mee, that am not able to ſtop one Wave. <hi>Atheneus</hi> reports,<note place="margin">Athen.</note> that the Theſſalians cleane raced
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:17163:104"/> downe a Citie of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans, becauſe it was named Flattery. I confeſſe, it were better with <hi>Diogenes</hi> to bid <hi>Alexander</hi> ſtand out of his light, and not deprive him of that, hee could not give him, then with <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> to ſpeake to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his heeles, inſtead of his eares. The World is full of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> his Schollers: Wee know too many <hi>Cliſophi,</hi> that will imitate <hi>Philip;</hi> And will not our Platoniſts array themſelves with Impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie inſteed of Modeſty?</p>
            <p>If our Eares muſt bee in our Heeles, there our Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants Tongues muſt dance attendance; If we could let them alone, where God hath placed them, they muſt packe up their Pipes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:17163:105"/> their Siege. Now Flattery hath ſo enwrapt it ſelfe into the skirts of Honeſty, that wee are <hi>Oves in fronte, vulpes in corde;</hi> The Cloake of Sanctitie covering the body of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, that makes me with the Poet, ſay
<q>
                  <l>Durum, ſed levius fit patientiâ</l>
                  <l>Quicquid corrigere eſt nefas.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Where ſhall <hi>Gyndanes</hi> find another <hi>Abaucus,</hi> who will carry out his wounded Friend, and leave his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to bee burnt: His Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Act is to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of. <hi>Incertum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>an hi boni ſint futuri, &amp;c.</hi> It is uncertaine, whether or
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:17163:105"/> no my Children will bee good hereafter, Hee hath beene long my Friend, and I ſhall hardly find out ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother as <hi>Gyndanes;</hi> Or where ſhall wee find ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pythias,</hi> whoſe love was ſuch, that (before that Tyrant <hi>Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>) the one dares to bee pledge for his Friends life, the other failes not the day of his Returne? What thinke you of <hi>Pilades,</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes? Niſus</hi> and <hi>Eurya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus? Perithous</hi> and <hi>Theſeus,</hi> whom Death it ſelfe could not ſeparate? or what of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> who in reſpect of their realty of Friendſhip were tranſlated into Stars? theſe were as the Verſes are.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:17163:106"/>
               <l>Alter ego niſi ſis, nec eris mihi verus amicus:</l>
               <l>Ni mihi ſis, ut ego, non eris alter ego.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And therefore a Friend is ſaid to bee <hi>Animi cuſtos,</hi> True Friendſhip is like Quick-ſilver put to Gold, which adheres ſo cloſe unto it, that it workes into its Intrals, and ſo farre incorporates it ſelfe, that both Mettals are become one Lumpe. Such Friendſhip there was in the Heroicke times, But now, Friends are as ſcarce as Beacons, they ſtand alone, and farre off one another: Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:17163:106"/> now-adayes marres Friendſhip and almoſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves Naturall Affection: So that I may tell you, If you have a Friend, to ſuſpect him unworthily, inſtructs him the next way to ſuſpect you, and prompts him even to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, Miſtruſt being that ſtifling Spirit, which inſinuates it ſelfe into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Action, or Paſſion of the Mind. Suſpicion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from ſelfe defect, and if thou doſt receive an Injury, Neglect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes with ſwifter Wings then Revenge; Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, all kind of Iealouſie is worſe then Frenzie, there may bee ſome end of the one, none of the other;
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:17163:107"/> Of all Paſſions no bitterer Potion. It begets unquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Mind, hunting after every Whiſper, and amplifying it with Intereſt, as that well skilled Maſter in Melancholy cals it.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Burt.</note>
               <l>Pale Hagge, infernall</l>
               <l>Fury, pleaſures ſmart,</l>
               <l>Envies Obſerver, prying in every Part.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Leave theſe ſuperfluous Thoughts which beget Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors to thy Soule. <hi>Iſocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> prayed, that hee might be ſafe from the danger of his Friends, rather then his Enemies, For that hee could beware of his enemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would not truſt them. I feare that now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes Friendſhip is like the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:17163:107"/> journy of the two Friends in the Fable, whom if the Beare meet, the one will fly to the Tree; while the other fals to the ground. Such, as this Traveller, are thoſe Friends, who wither in the Bud, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to the Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, not like the Indian Tree, which (as Hiſtory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports) never flouriſheth, but in the night, for whileſt the Sunne ſhineth it ſeemeth to Languiſh: nor reſembling Glo-wormes, which, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the day of Proſperity, reſerve their Splendor for the night of Adverſitie. Adverſitie being that Judge, which diſcovers our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and unmasketh our Friends.</p>
            <p>But are none to bee taxed with this Malady, but the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:17163:108"/> Laity? He were no injurious Patron, that ſhould herein taxe the Clergie too: But I am loath to pinch on the Parſons ſide: nor meane I any Reverend Miniſters, who make Conſcience of their wayes; but thoſe who terme themſelves Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, challenging that, which is none of their due, making Religion nothing, but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Knavery. If their Habit caracterize them not, yet you may know them by their Vſe and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and their Doctrine and Vſe, till there be no uſe of their Doctrine. Let them captivate the Illiterate, as Bees by the Baſon, if they liſt, For my part, I have done with them: let them with <hi>Aeſops</hi> Aſſe get on the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:17163:108"/> Lyons skinne, and terrifie the Flocke, they ſhall never cozen mee; I will play the Countrey-man in the ſame Fable, and tell him, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he bee, <hi>Vae mi aſelle, tàm benè novi, &amp;c.</hi> If any preciſer Idiots quarrell at my diſtaſt towards them, I paſſe them by as regardleſly, as Maſter <hi>Quarles</hi> in his Poem.<note place="margin">Quar.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>'Tis not thine eyes, which (taught to weepe by art)</l>
               <l>Looke red with teares (not guilty of the heart)</l>
               <l>'Tis not the holding of thy hands ſo high,</l>
               <l>Nor yet the purer ſquinting of thine Eye:</l>
               <l>'Tis not your Mimick mouthes, your Antick faces,</l>
               <l>Your Scripture-phraſes, or Affected Graces.</l>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:17163:109"/>
               <l>Nor Prodigall up-bending of thine eyes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe gaſhfull Balls doe ſeeme to pelt the Skies,</l>
               <l>'Tis not the ſtrickt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of your Haire</l>
               <l>So cloſe, that all the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Skull is bare.</l>
               <l>'Tis not the drooping of the Head ſo low,</l>
               <l>Nor yet the lowring of the ſullen Brow,</l>
               <l>Nor Woolviſh howling, that diſturbs the Aire,</l>
               <l>Nor Repetitions of your te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Prayer:</l>
               <l>No, no, 'tis none of theſe that God regards,</l>
               <l>Such ſort of Fooles their owne Applauſe rewards;</l>
               <l>Such holy Madneſſe God rejects and loathes,</l>
               <l>That ſinkes no deeper then the Skin and Clothes.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:17163:109"/>
            <p>Theſe kind of Birds were hatched of addle Egges elſe could they not have ſuch idle Heads; making Religion like the Law of <hi>Procruſtes</hi> among Theeves, with the Iron Bed cutting off al that were too long, and ſtretching forth all that were too ſhort. Their Conſcience for the moſt part, is without Wit, and if they have any Wit, 'tis without Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence making the ſacred Art of Pietie to bee the Bond of Iniquity. But they may take notice of the ingenious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of one, that ſaid Zeale without Wiſedome was like Mettle in a blind Horſe, which though it free the Rider from the toyle of the Spurre, yet it encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his labour in uſing the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:17163:110"/> Reines, leſt the Iades met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle becometh his owne, and his Riders overthrow. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva</hi> put a Golden bridle upon <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> that he ſhould not fly too faſt: and (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps upon this occaſion) the Emperor <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> did ſtamp in his Coine a Dolphin, and an Anchor, with this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe [Soon enough, if well enough.] A Dolphin outſtrips the Ship, that's ſoone enough, an Anchor ſtayes the Ship, that is well enough; a Dolphin and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, Soone enough, if well enough. Their mindes ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faſter then their horſes can gallop, muſt needs tire; Nor could their madneſſe ſo plainly appeare, did not the pride of their owne conceite raiſe up a duſt, which blinds
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:17163:110"/> them, otherwiſe ſhould I wonder that they ſhould not ſee the ſenſeleſneſſe of what they ſay, even whileſt they are ſpeaking. Whence comes it to paſſe, that our Pulpits are too often fraught rather with libellous Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quills, then with religious Meditations, but that theſe men have neither will to Learne, nor wit to Teach: outwardly demeaning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if Religion were quoted in their lookes, and Sanctity obliged to their ſervice. (Great difference there is betweene a Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and a Libeller.) And perhaps from hence Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> groundeth his ſpeech,<note place="margin">D. Greg.</note> That when they neglected to be the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Truth, they became
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:17163:111"/> the School-maſters of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. And thus much for the Religion of Raylers.</p>
            <p>Yet I would have none thinke that I owe a knee to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince I have read, ſhee is full of Imperfections. <hi>Angelo</hi> the famous Artizan of <hi>Italy</hi> may ſufficiently informe; who drawing the Pictures of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> for a Cardinall, a good Friend, and Benefactour of his, portrayed them with very red, and high coloured faces, whereas neither the Scripture, nor any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hiſtory, nor any Originall Tablet deſcribed them by any ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions: And being asked the Reaſon, becauſe (quoth hee) if they were now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:17163:111"/> they could not but bluſh at the Pompe of you Cardinals, the Pride of this Court, and the Abuſes of the Church in generall.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edwin Sandys</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Romane Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,<note place="margin">Sir Edwin Sandys.</note> eſpecially that of <hi>Italy,</hi> where it hath principally flouriſhed; ſaith, That they communicating Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Saints, and Angells, by building Churches, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting Altars, by worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their Images, going in Pilgrimage to their Relicks, attributing all kind of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, both to the one, and the other, have wrought this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall effect in thoſe parts; That men have more Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and aſſure unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a greater conceit of comfort, in the Patronage
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:17163:112"/> of the Creatures, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, then of God himſelfe, the Prime, and Creator. And touching the bleſſed Virgin, the caſe is cleare; That howſoever their Doctrine in Schooles bee otherwiſe, yet in all kind of outward Actions, the honour which they doe her is double (for the moſt part) unto that, they doe to our Saviour. Where one doth profeſſe himſelfe a Devoter, or peculiar Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of our Lord, whole Townes ſometimes (as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> by name) are Devoters of our Lady. Not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like this was the Storie of <hi>Gyovandria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Flor.</note> when he killed <hi>Galiazzo</hi> Duke of <hi>Millaine,</hi> who, after hee had heard Maſſe, turned towards the
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:17163:112"/> Image of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and ſaid, O <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Lord of our Citie, thou knoweſt our intentions, and the end, wherefore wee will adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture our ſelves to ſo many perils; Be favourable to this our Enterpriſe, and, by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of Iuſtice, ſhew how much Injuſtice doth diſpleaſe thee. If this will not ſerve turne, then hearken to the long diſpute between <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Machiavel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ig. Con.</note> for Superioritie in Hell, which may ſatisfie ſufficiently, the Devill himſelfe being Iudge, who gave the Precedencie to the Laity, and tooke it from the Clergy of <hi>Rome;</hi> he was forced to make much of the <hi>Machiavelians,</hi> becauſe they came ſeldome; but for the Ieſuits, they tumbled
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:17163:113"/> downe to Hell daily, eaſily, voluntarily, and by heapes, the Reaſon was added, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were accuſtomed to ſinne againſt their owne Conſciences. More might be urged of this Religion, but enough, unleſſe it were better: I will therefore cloſe up this Chapter with the words of our late King of peaceable memory.<note place="margin">K. Iames.</note> The Papiſts Religion is like <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> Iliads of the Siege of <hi>Troy,</hi> or <hi>Virgils Aeneads</hi> of the beginning of <hi>Rome;</hi> both of them had a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of truth, ſo had the Papiſts the Bible, but they have added ſo much, that the firſt Truth is almoſt loſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="199" facs="tcp:17163:113"/>
            <head>Of the firſt end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Subtilty tends, Riches. <hi>CAP. XIIII.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <l>Quid non mortalia pectora cogis,</l>
               <l>Auri ſacra fames?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND is it ſo, that we muſt have a voiage into Hell, with an <hi>Itum eſt in viſcera terra?</hi> If thou hadſt all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that lie hid in the Bowels of the Earth, envel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loped in the Concave of thine owne Belly, what would it gaine thee, thou Foole, if thou gaine the whole World, and looſe thine owne Soule? I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:17163:114"/> a Storie of a poore Man, who, for want of ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, tooke an Halter in his hand, with a reſolution to hang himſelfe; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the place, where he intended to bee his owne Executioner, found a Bagge of Gold, takes away the Gold, and leaves the Halter in the ſteed. He that hid the Gold, comming to the place, where hee left it, found it metamorphoſed into an Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, takes the Halter, and hangs himſelfe. Lord, what ſtrange effects this Gold workes: The one, for the want of it, would have han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelfe; the other for the loſſe of it, diſpatching his worke, did hang him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Mee thinkes <hi>Midas</hi> his eares ſhould forwarne us
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:17163:114"/> of ſuch Helliſh thrift. <hi>Midas</hi> the Image of a covetous Man, who, while he ſeekes to augment his Riches, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to himſelfe the uſe of his owne, and ſtarves in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance. And of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Verity, the Barbarous Indians had a naturall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who imagined that Gold was the God of the Spaniards, in that they hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after it ſo greedily. There is a Storie in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> not unlike,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> or unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the recitall, of one <hi>Pithius,</hi> an avaritious Prince, in the dayes of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> who exhauſted his Subjects in the diging and refining of Gold; whoſe Wife, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerating the cryes of the people, cauſed certaine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Worke-men, in the
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:17163:115"/> abſence of her Husband, to make a golden Table with variety of Viands, all of the ſame Mettall, which at his returne, ſhee cauſed to be ſet before him: Who long feaſting his eyes with ſo rare, and beloved a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, at length called for Meate to ſatisfie his hunger: When the like Artificiall Food was ſet before him, he in rage crying out, that hee was ready to famiſh, his Wife replyed, wee have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Sir, to entertaine you with but this; For while you employ the labour of the Citizens, and their Art in the getting of Gold, a number dye in the Mines, and all for that, which is leaſt uſefull, the Fields lye unculturated, the Vineyards
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:17163:115"/> undreſſed, the Orchards un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted; ſo that you muſt eate your Gold, or prevent the cauſe of this Scarcitie. Add to this that of <hi>Catiphus,</hi> Governour of the Citie of <hi>Suſa,</hi> who had therein a Tower full of Gold, and Iewels; but for Avarice would not diſperſe bis hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Treaſure amongſt his Souldiers; afterwards <hi>Alan</hi> King of the Tartarians, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed his Citie, and taking <hi>Catiphus</hi> ſhut him up in his Tower, ſaying unto him; If thou hadſt not ſo greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walled up this Treaſure, thou hadſt ſaved thy ſelfe, and this Citie: Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eate, and drinke, and take thy fill of that, thou loveſt ſo dearely, So died he miſerably through Famine
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:17163:116"/> in the midſt of exceſſive Riches. Obſerve that of <hi>Solon</hi> to <hi>Craeſus,</hi> who being asked of him, who was more happy then hee, ſince hee was <hi>Splendens auro &amp; gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis; Solon</hi> told three times, who was more happy: This three-fold Anſwer of <hi>Solon</hi> cauſed a triple wrath in <hi>Crae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> Indeed it was with <hi>Crae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> then, as it is with too many now, making many ſimple Converſions, Fooles Philoſophers, and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Fooles: but let them take heed with <hi>Craeſus,</hi> that they be not taken by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and led to the ſtake, and then being demanded of <hi>Cyrus;</hi> who that <hi>Solon</hi> is, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that he is not <hi>Vnus ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum,</hi> but <hi>Vnus ſapientum;</hi> And indeed his Anſwer was
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:17163:116"/> right; for
<q>
                  <l>Vltima ſemper</l>
                  <l>Expectanda dies homini eſt, dici<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> beatus,</l>
                  <l>Ante obitum nemo ſuprema<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> funera debet.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe then thou hadſt the goods of Fortune faſt locked in a Coffer; yet thy caſe may bee, as was this Kings of <hi>Lydia,</hi> who thought both God, and Men his Friends. To tell you, what Riches are, perhaps were frivolous, ſince others are better acquainted with them then my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>To attaine unto Riches. Many wayes we know unto this Wood, but the ordinary way is Vſurie which, though it bee forbidden in holy. Writ, and, I thinke, ſcarce
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:17163:117"/> allowed of by the Fathers; yet ſome good Authors have approved, that ſome kind of Vſurie may be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; ſome (certaine I am) is intolerable. I will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon the Point; onely acquaint you with the words of Biſhop <hi>Andrewes. Vſuras cum dico,</hi>
               <note place="margin">B. Andr.</note> 
               <hi>hoc dico, pactum ex mutuo lucrum; Tria haec (mutuum, lucrum, pactum) vim omnem faenoris appoſitè circumſcribunt.</hi> Yet I am not ſo preciſe, as hee that told a Holy Siſter, That ſhee ſhould lend, looking for nothing againe. So to cleare his Siſter from the Sinne of Vſury, he kept the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>But I come to treate of thoſe, which are Avaritious, whom I might yoke to Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars;
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:17163:117"/> You will ſay, That the linkes are unfit, one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made of Gold, and the other of Iron; Yet their conditions hold a fit Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie, both not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with any thing, before they dye; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I make this Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe there are Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, that <hi>Inter opes</hi> are <hi>mendici opum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Bernard.</note> Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> affirmes, That <hi>Avarus eſurit, ut Mendicus, Fidelis contemnit, ut Dominus; ille poſsidendo mendicat, iſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnendo ſervat;</hi> The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous man hungers, as a Beggar, the Faithfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnes it as a Lord; Hee by poſſeſſing begs, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by contemning poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Or more properly to the Eſtridge,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> That as <hi>Pliny</hi>
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:17163:118"/> reports, hath the wings of an Eagle, yet never mounts; Or they are like the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, who would not looſe his part in <hi>Paris,</hi> for his part in Paradiſe. Theſe men have an Itch, which hath alwayes need of clawing, Never ſatisfied, like <hi>Tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> in Hell; or like a Dog in a Wheele, which roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth meate for others ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; or like <hi>Ionathan,</hi> who for Hony-combs endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his life. And were not unſatisfied deſire too pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory for Counſell, too confident for diſlike, too po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for Remorſe, I would adviſe a man to live, as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi> preſcribes, <hi>Vt nec ſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè cuſtodiat, nec prodigè-ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat,</hi> That hee neither Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hoord up, nor Prodigally
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:17163:118"/> ſcatter it about, the one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominateth an ignoble mind, the other an improvident Indiſcretion; Spare not then, where Reputation lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth claime for Expence, nor expend, where Frugalitie with Moderation will ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and condemne thee of Prodigality, leſt thou be forced to looke Neceſſitie in the face; for to be a Banke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt is to bee a Thiefe in an Honourable kind. Living above Fortune is but to bee a Hiſtory to after times.</p>
            <p>Let thoſe Laviſhers then, that made the Covetous their Voyders, Live ſo thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, as to pay their debts in their life time, ſo may they deprive their Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of a trouble. And here, by the way, I meete a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:17163:119"/> among the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. The Ariſtotelians were of opinion, that Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of Riches might cauſe a tumult in a Common-wealth; Becauſe, if Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie and Riches ſhould chance to linke together (as too often they doe) then is great danger of <hi>Bellum ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile;</hi> I referre you for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to the Hiſtory of <hi>Florence:</hi> Your Platoniſts thought poverty the chiefeſt cauſe of Inſurrection in a Common-wealth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that old Saying, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitas non habet legem;</hi> For examples hereof, wee ſee them daily, though not dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly: Both which tenets among them are as yet unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled; If I might judge, I ſhould conceive the Golden
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:17163:119"/> meane the beſt: I need not here to bring in old Avarice to act its part, with <hi>Quo plus habet, eo plus cupit;</hi> or with <hi>Bonaventure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonav.</note> by way of compariſon, to liken it <hi>Orco, ſive Mari;</hi> Yet it might ſerve turne, ſince the Water of the one might quench the Fire of the other: I terme it old Avarice; Firſt, for its Antiquity; Next, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is moſt ſubject to old Age. And here I will tell you a Tale;<note place="margin">Guz.</note> When <hi>Iove</hi> had made the Fabrick of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, all things being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly good, before he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Man, the aſſes eyes being newly opened, he begins to leape and bray; At laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking himſelfe, why hee was made an Aſſe (it being proper to Aſſes to take the
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:17163:120"/> ends of things into their conſideration, when they are paſt remedy) hee came to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> to know where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was created; <hi>Iupiter</hi> told him, for the uſe of Man, and to performe his dutie and ſervice. The Aſſe, with his eyes ſet on the ground, demanded how long hee ſhould live in that ſlavery: <hi>Iupiter</hi> told him thirty yeares: He beſought <hi>Iupiter</hi> that hee might live but ten; and that hee would beſtow the other twenty yeares up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome other Creature, that were able to beare them: <hi>Iupiter</hi> condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the requeſt; The next living Creature that came to <hi>Iupiter</hi> was the Dogge, who partly underſtanding what had hapned betweene
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:17163:120"/> 
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> &amp; the Aſſe, after ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſoliciting for the curtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his dayes, it befell him, as it did the Aſſe; Whilſt the Fact was doing, the Ape did the like, and the like did happen to the Ape: Theſe things being finiſhed, <hi>Iupiter</hi> created Man, giving him power over all: Man, being deſirous to know the period of his dayes, deſired <hi>Iove,</hi> that hee might know how long hee ſhould live; <hi>Iupiter</hi> told him, that he had ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>ab Origine,</hi> thirty yeares to every living Creature, and that he was to enjoy no longer time; Man, being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of life, beſought that thoſe yeares, that theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had refuſed, might bee conferred on him, <hi>Iove</hi> yields to his requeſt: So Man lives
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:17163:121"/> (according to the Tale) thirty yeares; <hi>Quatenus</hi> he is a Man, in all uprightneſſe from the Preturbations of the World; from thirty to fifty, hee leads the life of an Aſſe, tumbling and turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for the things of this World; from fiftie to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventie, the Dogs refuſed yeares, ſnarling, grumbling, and envying at others; and, if he chance to live from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty to ninety, really poſſeſſed of the Apes twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hee will counterfeit the defects of Nature, uſing fooliſh and fantaſticall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes; and from thence I conceive the old Proverbe to ariſe, <hi>Senex bis puer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be asked, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Spirituality are not as well troubled with Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricious
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:17163:121"/> Infections, as the Temporality? I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on the Negative part; for I thinke if <hi>Aeſops</hi> Dogge ſhould bequeath his fiftie Pounds for a Legacie, hee ſhould never find any accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Clergy; yet Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> found fault with Simoniacall Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in his dayes,<note place="margin">Amb.</note> 
               <hi>Quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, cum Epiſcopus ordinare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aurum fuit, quod perdidit, anima fuit: cum alium ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naret, quod accepit, pecunia fuit, quod dedit, lepra fuit;</hi> That which hee gave (ſaith he) when hee was ordained Biſhop, was Gold, and that, which he loſt, was his ſoule: That, which he tooke, when hee ordained another, was mony; and that which hee gave, was Leproſie. It was
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:17163:122"/> ſtoutly,<note place="margin">B. Sandys.</note> and honeſtly ſpoken by Biſhop <hi>Sandys</hi> in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, whoſe words my wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes attend. If Simoniacall affection hath corrupted the heart of any Biſhop, it is not amiſſe, if his heart were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him in his hand, it is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delt with him, if he be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoped. And here perhaps it will be expected, I ſhould deſcend <hi>A majore ad minus,</hi> Something of the inferiour Levits, for their Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if not rather for their Simoniacall contracts: So that he that hath the greateſt Purſe, ſhall have the beſt Living. But, I hope, of this fault very few are guilty. As for your ingenious Clergy, they ſo handle the Cauſe, that all their actions are not, <hi>Propter privatum lucrum, ſed
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:17163:122"/> propter honorem Eccleſiae,</hi> howſoever ſuch Ingenuity, for the moſt part, is depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and Ignorance prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Certainely, there is an errour all over, but whether are moſt to blame, you may judge betweene the Doner, and the Donee; If one would not give, the other could not receive. But <hi>quo vado?</hi> I conclude on either ſide with a falſe verſe, though true ſenſe,
<q>Improbus ille Parſon, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis tu quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Patron.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let none ſet their hearts on worldly Riches, leſt they be ſerved, as the Rich Miſer, who having fild a Cheſt with bags of Gold, wrote on the top of it, <hi>Hic eſt Deus
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:17163:123"/> meus;</hi> A mad Knave being deſirous to ſee the Rich Mans God, broke open the Cheſt, and finding Gold, tooke it away; and, under <hi>Hic eſt Deus meus,</hi> wrote this Motto: <hi>Reſurrexit, non eſt hic. Anxiè quaeruntur, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilè cuſtodiuntur, adultimum omninò relinquuntur;</hi> They are doubtfully got (as you ſee) hardly kept, and at laſt, whether you will or not, to be left. <hi>Si divitiae effluxerint, non auferant niſi ſemetipſas;</hi> If Riches paſſe away from thee, let them carry nothing with them, but themſelves. Riches, without Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, are but the Fountaine of miſhap, they make young men Fooles, and old men Atheiſts- But, mee thinkes, wee are like the Young-man
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:17163:123"/> in the Goſpell: wee can ſay, wee can keepe all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, but wee are loath to part with our Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions: But by his favour, though hee would try a <hi>Niſi prius</hi> with our Saviour, yet he ſent his <hi>Mittimus</hi> along with him. It is eaſier for a Camell, &amp;c. <hi>Chryſologus</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> That <hi>Dives</hi> his Dogs were ſet to feare away Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, yet they licked <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his ſores; whence it may be noted, that Dogges are more naturally kind then ſome Rich Men. But all may take notice, that <hi>Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiam qui ſeminat inopi, ſibi metit; coeli pluvia infun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit terram, lachrymae paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum coelum rigant;</hi> Who ſowes Mercy to the Poore, mowes it to himſelfe; the
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:17163:124"/> Raine of Heaven refreſheth the Earth, the teares of the Poore water Heaven. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not here paſſe by <hi>Fulgentius</hi> his Compariſon,<note place="margin">Fulg.</note> betwixt the Rich Miſer, and the poore Beggar, without obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For <hi>Dives ille,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>purpurâ &amp; byſſo indutus, &amp; quotidiè ſplendidè epu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans, quam inanis fuit in illis epulis? quam pauper in multitudine divitiarum? quam nudus in pulchritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine veſtium? quam infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in ſanitate corporis? quam famelicus in ſaturitate ventris? quam miſer in gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs? quam deſolatus inter amicorum colloquia? quam dejectus inter obſequia ſervu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum? Attende contra La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarum in paupertate divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, in miſeriâ beatum, in
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:17163:124"/> infoelicitate foelicem, invulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ſanum, &amp; quidem ſine domo, ſed non ſine Domino; ſine veſte, ſed non ſine fide; ſine bonâ valetudine corporis, ſed non ſine robore charitatis; ſine cibo, ſed non ſine Chriſto; canibus expoſitum, ſed ſocium Angelorum; qui non accipie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat de micis, quae cadeba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t de menſâ divitis, ſed coeleſtem panem viſceribus ructabat ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternis;</hi> The Rich man was cloathed with Purple and fine Silke, and daily feaſted gloriouſly, but how emptie was hee amidſt his banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? how poore was hee in his riches? how naked in his beautifull garments? how infirme in the ſanity of his body? how emptie in the fulneſſe of his belly? how miſerable in his joyes?
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:17163:125"/> how deſolate in the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of his Friends? how deſtitute in the dutifulneſſe of his Servants? Marke againe <hi>Lazarus,</hi> Rich in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, Bleſſed in Miſery, Happy in Infelicity, Sound for all his Vlcers, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lord, though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Land-lord; without Rayment, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith; without the outward health of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but not without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtrength of Charity; without Meate, but not without Chriſt; expoſed to Dogs, yet accompanied with Angels; who did not receive the Crums, that fell from the Rich mans Table, but had his internall bowels glutted with the Bread of Heaven. Though the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:17163:125"/> be an Hoſpitall of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, yet (as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> very well obſerves) the fleſh of the Leper is as faire to God, as hee, that is bathed in Milke, and Spices. How often ſhall wee reade, <hi>Beati pauperes,</hi> in Holy Writ? but never, <hi>Totidem verbis, Beati divites.</hi> Miſtake mee nor, I am not of that common Opinion of thoſe, who ſay, <hi>Quo auctior in divitijs, eo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pioſior in vitijs.</hi> A man that is poore in Earthly treaſure, may thinke himſelfe rich in Heavenly; You may be both rich on Earth, and rich in Heaven, poore on Earth, and poore in Spirit towards Heaven. Wee know <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> hath his poore, and his rich Sonnes in his boſome. But mee thinkes, I heare the
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:17163:126"/> words of a Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Quiſque Dives, quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que pauper; nemo Dives, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo pauper, animus omnia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit;</hi> It is ſomewhat to be rich or poore, it is nothing to be rich or poore; it is as the mind is, the mind ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all.<note place="margin">D. Chryſ.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaking of what minde <hi>Dives</hi> carryed, gathered it out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> doubling and trebling, <hi>Tu, Tua, &amp; Tuâ recepiſti, tu, bona tua, in vitâ tuâ,</hi> which words are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king words, as hee concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and containe in them great Emphaſis, underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by <hi>Tua,</hi> not that ſo much, that hee had in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, as that, he had made ſpeciall reckoning of: For that is moſt properly ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ours. In a word, once
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:17163:126"/> againe, <hi>Animus omnia facit;</hi> Let mee then give this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat, that no man ſo farre dote on them, as (with <hi>Ahab</hi> at the perſwaſion of <hi>Iezebel</hi>) to ſell himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord, though hee be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to put on Sack-cloath and Aſhes to appeaſe the wrath of God; leſt the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Father in the Sonnes dayes fall upon the houſe. Or, with <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> for gaine to lie to the Holy-Ghoſt, leſt they fall downe dead at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles feet. Or laſt of all, with <hi>Iudas,</hi> for a ſmall Portion of Silver to ſell his Maſter, leſt they ſhould with <hi>Iudas,</hi> buy a Halter, and hang them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I conclude this with <hi>Architrenius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arch.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="226" facs="tcp:17163:127"/>
               <l>Inopſque,</l>
               <l>Plus animae, quam dives, habet, levioribus alis</l>
               <l>Pauper ad aſtra volat, dulcique pecunia mole,</l>
               <l>Quos aluit, laeſura premit, nec Craeſus in auro</l>
               <l>Fata fugit, perdenſque Deos non perditur umbris.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="227" facs="tcp:17163:127"/>
            <head>Of the ſecond end, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Subtilty tends, Honour. <hi>CAP. XV.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd now of Honor; which <hi>Aristotle</hi> termes <hi>Benefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae gloriae initium.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aquin.</note> That Honour is <hi>Cujuſlibet virtutis praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> If I ſhould here tell you, where this matchleſſe Lady Honour keepeth her ſeate, you may marvell at my preſumptuous Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. Some thinke in the Soule onely, or elſe in the Soule and Body together: ſome in Prudence, others in Goodneſſe of maners; but I thinke all Nobility hath
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:17163:128"/> its Originall from Virtue; True Nobility being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Bloud, Virtue, and Power. Queſtionleſſe, Kings never made any Noble-man <hi>Propter Lucrum;</hi> but as they thought, <hi>Propter Meritum;</hi> Perhaps ſome by By-wayes may buy Honour, but thoſe, that enjoy it ſo, reape onely the commendations of good Polititians: For what they give in Money, for the moſt part, they ſave in Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. And herein (by the way) thoſe Heraulds may be blamed, who Honour, where it is not due, and ſhape ſo many new Coats for upſtart Gentlemen. In this have they no way to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd a Cenſure, but to compound with <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>America</hi> to produce more
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17163:128"/> Monſters, or elſe they muſt make fewer Gentlemen. Vaine Honour is but the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll of Fooles, for no wiſe man ever ſought felicity in ſhadowes.<note place="margin">Eurip.</note> Indeed <hi>Euripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> ſaith, The honeſt-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man is onely Noble, and not he, that deſcendeth of ancient Race. For wee know, in proceſſe of time, though the ſtallion be good, yet, by the Mares fault, the breed may alter, and ſo prove Jades. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe valiant <hi>Ephricates</hi> a Shoo-makers Sonne, being upbraided by <hi>Hermodius</hi> a Peere, told him, my bloud takes its beginning from me, and thine from thee its fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well. Obſerve <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec.</note> Hee firſt askes you a Queſtion, then gives you his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:17163:129"/> 
               <hi>Quis generoſus? Ad virtutem a naturâ benè com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitus animus facit nobilem, cui ex quacunque conditione ſupra fortunam licet ſurgere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as I ſhall herein juſtly commend <hi>Seneca;</hi> ſo ſhall I not unjuſtly taxe the too ſevere Cenſure of <hi>Saluſt</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Nobility of his time in generall,<note place="margin">Saluſt.</note> When hee thus upbraids them, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptor animus, &amp; ſuperbia commune nobilitatis malum;</hi> For where ſhall wee ſee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative Arrogancy more ſetled, then in an upſtart Gentleman?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. Flor.</note>True it is, that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of <hi>Florence</hi> had once ſo ill behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the Citizens made a Decree; That, if any one had received a blow,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:17163:129"/> or loſſe in goods, the party damnified might call him to the Councels, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt him for one of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; ſo odious was the name. Among the Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Romanes, they joyned the Temple of Virtue to the Temple of Honour, and ſo linked them together, that whoſoever would come to the Temple of Honour, muſt firſt paſſe through the Temple of Virtue. Boaſt not then thy ſelfe of thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable place, but ſee, that thou be juſtly worthy of it; uſe rather the Spurs of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, then the Stirrops of Inſolency.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe, Honour is a good Brooch to weare in a mans Hat yet in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wiſe men ſomtimes &amp; fooles, take
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:17163:130"/> their Fortune. Every man knowes, that <hi>Lubrica eſt ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la fortunae,</hi> Slippery is the Ladder of Fortune; and <hi>Quò altiùs ſcandis, eò gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viùs cadis;</hi> The higher thou climbeſt, the more dangerous is thy fall; and the higher thou groweſt, the more ſubject to the danger of Windes; Why doſt thou then waxe proud, thou fraile earth and aſhes? Wee have read, that <hi>Caeſar cum pompâ, Alexander cum Sceptro ceci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit;</hi> Ambition is like a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that never lookes backe. Run then an eaſie Current, not over high, take not an Inventory of thine owne worth, nor wing thy thoughts with too high fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Feathers, leſt they ſpread themſelves ſo wide,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:17163:130"/> as to cover thy little world with their Shadowes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of <hi>Icarus.</hi> Was it not <hi>Plinies</hi> Pride to finde out the ſecrets of <hi>Aetna?</hi> and what became of him? wee reade it was his ruine. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what became of that Tyrant <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtript out of his Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was glad to play the Schoolemaſter at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and inſtead of a Scepter, bore a Rod, ſo that of a cruell Tyrant, hee became a frowning Pedant. Or that Ruler <hi>Bladud,</hi> or <hi>Baldud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Graft.</note> who by his Necromanticke Art, and <hi>Daedalion</hi>-like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to fly, falling, broke his necke at <hi>Troy-no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> now <hi>London.</hi> Nay, goe to the Text, and you ſhall finde that Pride was
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:17163:131"/> the downe-fall of <hi>Babel,</hi> the Gallowes for <hi>Haman,</hi> the butcher for <hi>Nichanor,</hi> the conſumption of <hi>Herod,</hi> the deſtruction of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and was not, for the ſame offence <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and his hoaſt drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the red Sea? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the words of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Quid tu igitur ſuperbis, terra et cinis? Si ſuperbtentibus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis Deus non pepercit, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tò minùs tibi, putredo et vermis? Nihil ille Lucifer fecit, nihil operatus eſt, tantùm cogitavit ſuperbiam, &amp; in momento, in ictu oculi irrecuperabiliter ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratus eſt;</hi> What therefore wouldeſt thou have proud earth &amp; aſhes? If God hath not ſpared the Pride of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, how much leſſe the pride of Man, who is but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction and a worme? <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi>
               <pb n="235" facs="tcp:17163:131"/> did nothing, wrought nothing, onely he had proud imaginations, and in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the twinckling of an Eye, hee is irrecoverably ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the bleſſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Angels, <hi>Si igitur Diabolus propter ſuperbiam de coelo dejectus eſt, multò minùs, ſuperbus illic non intrabit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bad.</note> If therefore (ſaith <hi>Badeus</hi>) the Devill for Pride was caſt out of Heaven, how then is it poſſible, that a proud man ſhould enter therein?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neque enim deberent ultrà coelum aſpicere, qui in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem coeli peccaverunt, &amp; dominum Majeſtatis;</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed (ſaith <hi>Origen</hi>) ought their Pride to behold Heaven,<note place="margin">Orig.</note> who have ſinned againſt Heaven, and the Lord of Majeſty.</p>
            <pb n="236" facs="tcp:17163:132"/>
            <p>And note, <hi>Superbia dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur initium omnis peccati, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici ratione. Primò, propter cauſam, quae invenitur in omni peccato, quia in omni peccato invenitur contemptus dei, qui eſt quaedam cauſa peccati, iſte autem contemptus eſt averſio à creatore: ſecundò, quià pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum peccatum fuit: Tertiò, quià ex eo naſcuntur alia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſecundum prius &amp; poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, hoc eſt, mediatè, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatè;</hi> Pride is ſayd to bee the beginning of every ſinne, for a three-fold rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Firſt, for the cauſe, which is found out in every ſinne, becauſe in every ſinne appeares the contempt of God, which is a certaine cauſe of ſinne; and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt is a proud Averſion from the Creator. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:17163:132"/> becauſe it was the firſt Sinne. Thirdly, becauſe other vices are begot from this <hi>Secundum prius &amp; poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius;</hi> That is, mediately, or immediately, as you may reade more at large in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes de Combis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. de Comb.</note> True hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe ſtands not either in Riches, or Honour, or any kind of terreſtriall thing. Doe not then like the Day-labourer lift up thy hands to Heaven, and ſtrike thy Mattocke into the ground. Be not like <hi>Plinies</hi> Eagle, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one Foote ſhut <hi>more Anſeris,</hi> whereby he ſwims; another ſharpe after the manner of Eagles, whereby hee ſnatcheth; have not <hi>Cum pede aquilino pedem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerinum;</hi> Worldly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons joyned with ſpirituall.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:17163:133"/>
               <l>Theſe two things doe para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell as ill,</l>
               <l>As an Eagles Feather and a Gooſe quill</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note>
               <hi>Ioſephus</hi> is ſo farre from theſe feete of two Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that <hi>Prius-quàm inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias communem habere cibum, magnis execrationibus adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat te primùm colere Deum;</hi> Before thou beginneſt to take thy common ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, hee adjures thee with great execrations, that thou firſt praiſe God.<note place="margin">Theod.</note> And <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doricus</hi> invites us to this Action by the example of the Dove, <hi>Columba, quùm ſingula grana roſtro deglutit, roſtrum &amp; oculos in altum, Deo quaſi gratias actura, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollit. Accipit unum granum,
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:17163:133"/> &amp; oculos in altum elevat, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit alterum, tertium, &amp; quartum, &amp; ſic demùm ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litèr ad ſingula grana facit;</hi> The Dove, when ſhee takes up with her Beake ſeverall Granes, lifts up her Beake, and eyes towards Heaven, as if to give God thankes; ſhe receives one Grane, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levates her eyes on high, ſhe receives an other, and againe ſtirs up her eyes, ſhe receives a third, and a fourth, and ſo in like manner ſhee doth for every Grane: And now he comes with a <hi>Quidni ergo &amp; nos, ad ſingula Dei benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, oculos, &amp; corda ſurſùm attolleremus, &amp; benefactori noſtro optimo gratias agere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus?</hi> And ſhall not we then lift up our eyes and hearts for the ſeverall benefits, we
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:17163:134"/> have received from God, and give thankes to our beſt Benefactour? Haſt thou with <hi>Adam,</hi> by the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans temptations offended in Paradiſe; Haſt thou with <hi>Noah,</hi> by overmuch tipling, been overcome with Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe; Haſt thou with <hi>Herod</hi> for a Dancing Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſell cut off <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> Head; Haſt thou with <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> by the allurement of ſtrange Women worſhipped Idols; Haſt thou with <hi>Lot,</hi> taken ſo much: of the Grape, as to lead thee to an inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bed; or haſt thou with <hi>David,</hi> got a Pearle in one Eye, and the other blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhotten: Pray then with him, that thy eyes be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that thou maiſt ſee thy wayes; For when thou ſeeſt
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:17163:134"/> another ſuffer for thoſe ſinnes, whereof thou art guilty, art thou not then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by Atturnie? Pray therefore in ſeaſon, and (if it were poſſible) out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; For how can it bee preſumed, that God ever thought of one, that never dreamt of him? Let not thy Prayer bee like <hi>Ionas</hi> Gourd; grow up in one day, and periſh in another. Let not then the Cinque-ports of thy ſenſes allow of ſuch enticing inlets, as may make thee a Slave to Satan. Let not thine Iniquity be frozen in Errour, nor benummed in the cuſtome thereof, leſt from Suggeſtion ſhould iſſue Cogitation; from Cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Affection; from Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction Delectation; from De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:17163:135"/> Conſent; from Conſent Action; from Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Cuſtome; from Cuſtome Obſtinacie; from Obſtinacie Hardneſſe of heart; from Hardneſſe of heart, Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; from Boaſting Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration; from Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Damnation. Mans Soule is a precious Iewell, his Body the Cabinet, hee the Keeper of both. And, ſince hee is the Salt-celler of his owne Soule (the Soule being impriſoned in the fleſh) hee ſhould not ſuffer Ill-ſeaſoned thoughts to uſher him to ill Actions, leſt by an helliſh Arithmeticke, hee make one ſinne a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. For let him be aſſured, the firſt fruits of evill will bee puniſhed in this World, the After-crop hee muſt
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:17163:135"/> leave to God. Serve then thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">Plin.</note> as <hi>Plinies</hi> Pigmies doe the Cranes, deſtroy them in the ſhels; or, at leaſt-wiſe, aſſoone as they are hatched, leſt they grow to multitudes, and then it will prove a hard matter to over-come them.<note place="margin">Zanc.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> obſerves in his Booke, <hi>De operibus Dei,</hi> that the Devill hath twelve ſeverall names in the Hebrew, and twenty and one in the Greeke text, and all either of <hi>Seduciae</hi> or <hi>Aſtutiae.</hi> We know the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill had foure ſeverall fields, wherein hee might exerciſe the part of a cunning Seedſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. In Heaven, as it is in <hi>Eſayah;</hi> In Paradiſe with the Woman, as it is in <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis;</hi> In the Church, as it is now; And laſtly, in every
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:17163:136"/> Mans heart.<note place="margin">D. Chryſ.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> makes a Compariſon betweene the Devill, and a Dogge; for (ſaith hee) as a Dogge waiting at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if you give him any thing, will ſtill waite for more; if nothing, hee will depart: So the Devill, if once you make much of him, he will waite diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for farther Courteſies; but if you reject him, hee will forbeare his temptations. Man is in perpetuall Action, where <hi>Non progredi eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi; non procedere recedere eſt;</hi> For goodneſſe without perſeverance, is like an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacke out of date. Wee are like Spring-locks, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to ſhut, then to open, to ſhut goodneſſe from us, then to receive it to us: Or like
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:17163:136"/> looſe Stones on the tops of Hils, willing enough to tumble downe, but ſlow enough to mount up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ayde. Like the Bird, that Saint <hi>Anſelme</hi> found tyed to a Stone,<note place="margin">D. Anſel.</note> which no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner mounted, but preſently was puld backe: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red teares from this Holy Father, who bewailed the miſerable eſtate of man, who endeavours by the Spirit to flye to Heaven, yet is ſtopt by the Fleſh. It is with men, as it is with Raſpiſſes, one Stalke grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, another growne up, and a third withered. Or as with Flowers: Grow up, Seed, and dye. Like the three Siſters of Deſtiny, <hi>Clotho, Lacheſis,</hi> and <hi>Atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos:</hi>
               <pb n="246" facs="tcp:17163:137"/> The firſt ſpinning, the ſecond drawing out, and the third cutting off the Thread of mans life. Men are like billowes of the Sea, which tumble, one after another, till they come to the Shoare. Or like water powred out of a Bucket, which the earth quickly ſucketh up, and it appeareth not againe. Or (if you will) like a Glaſſe-houſe, wherein no man knowes what Glaſſe ſhall firſt be broken, but hee that owes the houſe. Plaine then it is, That wee muſt dy; the Poet can tell us, That there is no Redemption from Death,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Hor.</note>Non ſi tricenis, quotquot eunt dies,</l>
                  <pb n="247" facs="tcp:17163:137"/>
                  <l>(Amice) places illachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabilem</l>
                  <l>Plutona tauris.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hence is it,<note place="margin">Iuv.</note> that <hi>Iuvenall</hi> playes with the danger of Mariners, and concludes them not certaine of an houres Leaſe of their lives, becauſe at all times there is but an Inch betwixt them, and Death. And aptly doth my Kinſman tranſlate the danger of one under Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke in his <hi>Ovid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">George Sandys.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>Art failes, Hart ſinks, on every riſing Wave</l>
                  <l>Death ſits in Triumph, and preſents a Grave.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="248" facs="tcp:17163:138"/>
            <p>It is concluded, that wee muſt dye; obſerve then the rule of <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen.</note> Who, in his Youth, exerciſed the Art <hi>Benè vivendi;</hi> and in his Age, <hi>Benè moriendi;</hi> For thy life is like a Journey, the lighter thy Burden, the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier thy Journey. Life is but a Parentheſis in a long Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, and who knowes, what will become of us, till wee heare that Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, <hi>Venite Benedicti,</hi> or <hi>Abite maledicti;</hi> Let the heart then of each Chriſtian embrace Saint <hi>Bernards</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie, which, if Story lye not, ſtandeth in this manner on his Tombe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tria vobis, fratres, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanda relinquo, quae, ut po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui, obſervavi. Primò, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſcandalum feci, ſi quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:17163:138"/> incidit, ſedavi, ut potui. Secundò, Minùs ſemper ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſui meo, quam alterius cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi. Tertiò, Laeſus de laeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te nunquàm vindictam petij. Ecce, Charitatem, Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. Patientiam vobis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquo;</hi> Brethren (ſaith he) there be three things, that I bequeath to your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which, aſwell as I could, I have obſerved my ſelfe; Firſt, I never gave ſcandall to any perſon, if any ſcandall happened, I pacified the matter to my power. Secondly, I ſtood upon mine owne conceite leſſe, then I did upon other mens. Thirdly, when I was, wronged, I never ſought Revenge. Behold, Charity, Humilitie, and Patience I bequeath unto you.</p>
            <pb n="250" facs="tcp:17163:139"/>
            <p>What was ſaid of all the Kings, that were mentioned in the Hebrew Text? They lived, they dyed, Well or Ill. For our parts let us live, that wee may dye; dye, that wee may live. For, as there is no <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> from death; ſo, no <hi>Habeas Animam</hi> from Hell: that remaines for ever.</p>
            <p>Each man is a Comedian, Acts his Part, then to the Tiring houſe, and ther's an end; Snore not then ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinely in the ſtate of ſinne; Let us expect the firſt houre of the day to be the houre of our death; <hi>Brevis eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra paſsionis, ſequitur gloria ſempiterna;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fer.</note> As <hi>Ferus</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. Let every Third thought be thy Grave, and climbe up by the rounds of
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:17163:139"/> Contemplation into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Mentem in ſublimi ſupra illum eximium coeli globum defixam habe.</hi> Death is but the Orient of Weale, and the Occident of Woe; The upriſing of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the downe-ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Perturbation; The deliverer from Servitude, the curer of Cares, the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to Paine, the Porter to Paradiſe, and the condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to the Deity. Thinke not then of any worldly thing, for all comes within the compaſſe of Vanitie, and vexation of the Spirit; And whoſoever thinkes any Temporall thing to be <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum,</hi> faſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city but to a rotten Cable. Only think thou of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver bleſſed name, <hi>Ieſus,</hi> which
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:17163:140"/> is <hi>Mel in ore, In aure melos, &amp; in corde Iubilum.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with thoſe old but true Verſes,
<q>
                  <l>Si tibi pulchra domus, ſi ſplendida menſa; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si ſpecies auri, argenti quoque maſſa; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si tibi ſponſa decens, ſi ſit generoſa; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si tibi ſint nati, ſi praedia magna; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si fueris pulcher, fortis, diveſque; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si longus ſervorum inſerviat ordo; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si doceas alios in qualibet arte; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si faveat mundus, ſi proſpera cuncta; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Si Prior, aut Abbas, ſi Rex, ſi Papa; quid inde?</l>
                  <pb n="253" facs="tcp:17163:140"/>
                  <l>Si rota fortunae te tollat ad aſtra; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Annos ſi foelix regnes per mille; quid inde?</l>
                  <l>Tam citò, tam citò praetereunt haec, &amp; nihil inde,</l>
                  <l>Sola manet virtus, quâ glorificabimur inde,</l>
                  <l>Ergo Deo ſervi, quià tunc tibi provenit inde,</l>
                  <l>Quod feciſſe voles in tempore, quo morieris,</l>
                  <l>Hoc facias juvenis, dum corpore ſanus haberis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:141"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:141"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF each ſeverall <hi>Chapter.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP I.</label>
               <item>AN Introduction to the <hi>Foure Cardinall Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. pag. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>The Originall of all Virtue, whence it ſprings. <hi>pag. 26.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17163:142"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>The true Subject of Virtue, to whom it properly belongs. <hi>pag. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>The Definition of Prudence, The firſt of the foure Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Virtues. <hi>pag. 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>The Definition and ſeverall Branches of Prudence. <hi>pag. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>Of Memory the firſt part of Prudence. <hi>pag. 63.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17163:142"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Of the Vnderſtanding, the Intellectuall part, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Branch of Prudence. <hi>pag. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>Of Providence; the third part of Prudence. <hi>pag. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
               <item>Of the generall Duties of Providence, and firſt of the Mutuall Reſpect betweene Kings and their Subjects. <hi>pag. 112</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17163:143"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Of the Mutuall Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Parents and their Children. <hi>pag. 126.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XI.</label>
               <item>Of the Mutuall Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Maſters and their Servants. <hi>pag. 161.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XII.</label>
               <item>Of the Subtilty of the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, by ſome eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Branch of Prudence, but indeed an Appendix to its Intellectuall part. <hi>pag. 167</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17163:143"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Of divers Ends of the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings Subtilty, and meanes thereto; and firſt of the High-way Flattery. <hi>pag. 170.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XIV.</label>
               <item>Of the firſt End, whereunto Subtilty tends, Riches. <hi>pag. 199.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XV.</label>
               <item>Of the ſecond end, whereunto Subtilty tends, Honour. <hi>pag. 227.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:144"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17163:144"/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for WILLIAM SHEARES. 1634.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
